
========== Taufique 绛?- 2025 - HiDPHierarchical DNN Partitioning for Distributed Inference on Heterogeneous Edge Platforms - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L039: models on commercial edge devices. On average our strategy | achieved 38% lower latency, 46% lower energy, and 56% higher | throughput in comparison with other relevant approaches.
  L061: Typically, edge nodes are composed of heterogeneous pro- | cessing units including CPU, GPU, and Neural Processing | Units (NPUs), exhibiting a high degree of compute diversity
  L074: multi-core edge node, leading to sub-optimal inference latency. | For example, TensorFlow [18] schedules inference on GPU by | default, unless explicitly specified by the application to use
  L077: other CPUs/NPUs [19], [20]. Running inference on a single | processing unit (e.g. GPU) misrepresents the compute capacity | of the local heterogeneous edge node, resulting in sub-optimal
  L086: Adapting heterogeneity-aware DNN scheduling techniques | for distributed inference requires intelligent orchestration to | jointly optimize DNN partitioning and workload distribution,
  L090: cision control transfer. However, existing distributed inference | strategies lack such intelligent orchestration. | We demonstrate the limitations of existing distributed infer-
  L092: We demonstrate the limitations of existing distributed infer- | ence techniques over four DNN models run on the Jetson TX2 | platform [23]. Figure 1 shows normalized inference latency of
  L097: a specific combination of (i) number of data-wise partitions | of the DNN model and (ii) CPU-GPU workload split. Among | these configurations, P1 is the default TensorFlow workload
  L098: of the DNN model and (ii) CPU-GPU workload split. Among | these configurations, P1 is the default TensorFlow workload | scheduling choice 鈥?running inference exclusively on the
  L100: scheduling choice 鈥?running inference exclusively on the | GPU with no data partitioning. State-of-the-art distributed | inference techniques use the workload partitioning configu-
-- page 2 --
  L004: partitioning configurations other than P1, where the inference | workload is partitioned and split between the CPU and GPU. | Latency of ResNet-152 and VGG-19 are lowest at P7 (4
  L005: workload is partitioned and split between the CPU and GPU. | Latency of ResNet-152 and VGG-19 are lowest at P7 (4 | data partitions with 80% workload on GPU and 20% on
  L006: Latency of ResNet-152 and VGG-19 are lowest at P7 (4 | data partitions with 80% workload on GPU and 20% on | CPU), InceptionNet-V3 at P6 (90% workload with 2 data
  L007: data partitions with 80% workload on GPU and 20% on | CPU), InceptionNet-V3 at P6 (90% workload with 2 data | partitions on GPU and 10% workload with 4 data partitions
  L008: CPU), InceptionNet-V3 at P6 (90% workload with 2 data | partitions on GPU and 10% workload with 4 data partitions | on CPU), and EfficientNet-B0 at P9 (4 data partitions and
  L009: partitions on GPU and 10% workload with 4 data partitions | on CPU), and EfficientNet-B0 at P9 (4 data partitions and | 50% workload split between CPU and GPU). InceptionNet-
  L010: on CPU), and EfficientNet-B0 at P9 (4 data partitions and | 50% workload split between CPU and GPU). InceptionNet- | V3, ResNet-152, VGG-19, and EfficientNet-B0 have 65%,
  L011: 50% workload split between CPU and GPU). InceptionNet- | V3, ResNet-152, VGG-19, and EfficientNet-B0 have 65%, | 40%, 25%, and 75% lower latency respectively, in comparison
  L014: with existing distributed inference strategies using the default | TensorFlow run-time. It should be noted that optimal parti- | tioning configuration (number of partitions and workload split
  L016: tioning configuration (number of partitions and workload split | between CPU and GPU) differs for different DNN models. Our | analysis highlights that the default partitioning configuration
  L039: distribution, and scheduling of DNN inference services | 鈥?Evaluation of HiDP strategy against existing distributed | inference techniques on real hardware edge cluster setup
  L041: inference techniques on real hardware edge cluster setup | including Jetson Orin NX, Jetson Nano, Jetson TX2, | Raspberry Pi 4B, and Raspberry Pi 5.
  L042: including Jetson Orin NX, Jetson Nano, Jetson TX2, | Raspberry Pi 4B, and Raspberry Pi 5. | The paper is organized as follows: Section II provides
  L081: 1 and 2. Within devices 1 and 2, the inference blocks are | executed on GPU by default. As presented empirically in Fig- | ure 1, this partitioning configuration leads to longer inference
-- page 3 --
  L024: Unlike the State-of-the-Art (SoA) strategies, HiDP considers | latency and energy reduction through hierarchical partitioning. | III. HIDP FRAMEWORK
  L028: tributed DNN inference across heterogeneous edge clusters. | The nodes are connected via wireless networks and can | collaborate at run-time to perform inference tasks. The DNN
  L104: selects data partitioning and splits the workload following | heterogeneity of two CPUs and one GPU. The Run-time | scheduler gets the local and global results via Communication
  L116: allocates the workload to the desired processing units. The OS | allows run-time monitoring of the board鈥檚 power consumption | through onboard sensors or external power monitoring equip-
  L117: allows run-time monitoring of the board鈥檚 power consumption | through onboard sensors or external power monitoring equip- | ment to measure the energy consumption of a DNN inference.
  L118: through onboard sensors or external power monitoring equip- | ment to measure the energy consumption of a DNN inference. | Workloads. We design HiDP to handle DNN inference re-
-- page 4 --
  L024: node. For each node, there exist k processors such that | 蠒 = {蟻1, 蟻2, ..., 蟻k} where 蟻k represents CPU, GPU, or NPU. | We denote the computation frequency of a processor as fk
  L054: overhead between two nodes for a given time duration t via | a wireless network. HiDP calculates the communication rate | of each node by sending a set of pseudo packets to each node
-- page 5 --
  L034: Execute state, and (iii) report back the results to the leader. | IV. EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION | A. Experimental Setup
  L035: IV. EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION | A. Experimental Setup | Evaluation Platform. We design a collaborative heteroge-
  L036: A. Experimental Setup | Evaluation Platform. We design a collaborative heteroge- | neous edge cluster, comprising commercial edge platforms
  L039: (shown in Table II), and deploy the HiDP strategy on the | defined platform. We monitor the run-time power consumption | of the Jetson boards using the on-board power sensors. We use
  L040: defined platform. We monitor the run-time power consumption | of the Jetson boards using the on-board power sensors. We use | the external shunt resistor to monitor the power consumption
  L041: of the Jetson boards using the on-board power sensors. We use | the external shunt resistor to monitor the power consumption | of the Raspberry Pi boards.
  L042: the external shunt resistor to monitor the power consumption | of the Raspberry Pi boards. | Workloads. We evaluated our framework over widely used
  L044: Workloads. We evaluated our framework over widely used | DNN models of ResNet152, EfficientNetB0, VGG-19, and | InceptionNetV3. We implemented these models using the
  L045: DNN models of ResNet152, EfficientNetB0, VGG-19, and | InceptionNetV3. We implemented these models using the | TensorFlow library [18], with input image sizes of 224x224,
  L046: InceptionNetV3. We implemented these models using the | TensorFlow library [18], with input image sizes of 224x224, | TABLE II
  L048: TABLE II | TECHNICAL SPECIFICATIONS OF THE EVALUATION SETUP | Device
  L051: CPU | GPU | DRAM
  L053: DRAM | Jetson Orin NX | 8x ARM Cortex-A78
  L057: 8 GB | Jetson TX2 | 2x Denver-2, 4x ARM Cortex-A57
  L061: 8 GB | Jetson Nano | 4x ARM Cortex-A57
  L065: 4 GB | Raspberry Pi 5 | 2x ARM Cortex-A76
  L067: 2x ARM Cortex-A76 | VideoCore VII | 4 GB
  L069: 4 GB | Raspberry Pi 4 | 2x ARM Cortex-A72
  L071: 2x ARM Cortex-A72 | VideoCore VI | 4 GB
  L079: We used CGroup libraries to bind the workload to the desired | number of CPU cores. For GPU implementation, the Ten- | sorFlow backend used CUDA libraries for NVIDIA boards
  L080: number of CPU cores. For GPU implementation, the Ten- | sorFlow backend used CUDA libraries for NVIDIA boards | and OpenCL for Raspberry Pi boards. All the devices are
  L081: sorFlow backend used CUDA libraries for NVIDIA boards | and OpenCL for Raspberry Pi boards. All the devices are | connected over 80 MBps wireless control through POSIX-
  L082: and OpenCL for Raspberry Pi boards. All the devices are | connected over 80 MBps wireless control through POSIX- | based client-server architecture. We used multi-threaded server
  L096: Carlo search tree and pipelines the DNN inference over both | CPU and GPU. We implemented the throughput estimator of | Omniboost using Gymnasium library [25] and trained it on
  L110: latency, | throughput, energy consumption (based on run-time power | monitoring), and accuracy as evaluation metrics. Figure 5 (a)
-- page 6 --
  L001: Fig. 5. | Inference (a). latency and (b). energy consumption of different | strategies for targeted DNN workloads.
  L005: targeted DNN workloads. | latency of HiDP strategy also reflects in the lowest energy | consumption for all the workloads. HiDP consumes upto
  L007: consumption for all the workloads. HiDP consumes upto | 67%, 59%, 54%, and 54% lower energy for EfficientNet, | inceptionNet, ResNet, and VGG against relevant strategies. On
  L008: 67%, 59%, 54%, and 54% lower energy for EfficientNet, | inceptionNet, ResNet, and VGG against relevant strategies. On | average HiDP consumes 33%, 48%, and 58% lower energy
  L009: inceptionNet, ResNet, and VGG against relevant strategies. On | average HiDP consumes 33%, 48%, and 58% lower energy | than DisNet, OmniBoost, and MoDNN, respectively.
  L014: with successive run-time inference requests for every 0.5s, | in the order of EfficientNetB0, InceptionNetV3, ResNet152, | and VGG-19. This creates a progressively increasing workload
  L015: in the order of EfficientNetB0, InceptionNetV3, ResNet152, | and VGG-19. This creates a progressively increasing workload | such that at t=1.5s, all four DNNs are running concurrently on
  L055: latency than DisNet, OmniBoost, and MoDNN, respectively. | For VGG-19, EfficientNetB0, ResNet-152, and InceptionNet- | V3, HiDP has an average Top-1% accuracy of 75.3%, 77.1%,
  L067: followed by optimized partitioning and scheduling on a local | heterogeneous edge node. We evaluated HiDP on four Jetson | platforms and two Raspberry Pi platforms achieving latency
  L068: heterogeneous edge node. We evaluated HiDP on four Jetson | platforms and two Raspberry Pi platforms achieving latency | and energy improvements of 38%, and 46% against SoA
  L069: platforms and two Raspberry Pi platforms achieving latency | and energy improvements of 38%, and 46% against SoA | strategies, respectively.
-- page 7 --
  L004: Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications and Services, 2022. | [2] J. Kim et al., 鈥淓nergy-aware scenario-based mapping of deep learning | applications onto heterogeneous processors under real-time constraints,鈥?
  L009: inference on resource-constrained IoT edge clusters,鈥?IEEE Trans. on | Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, 2018. | [4] J. Mao et al., 鈥淢oDNN: Local distributed mobile computing system for
  L033: big. little multicore processors,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided | Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, vol. 39, no. 10, 2019. | [11] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization
  L034: Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, vol. 39, no. 10, 2019. | [11] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization | for power-efficient dnn inference,鈥?in 2023 IEEE/ACM International
  L035: [11] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization | for power-efficient dnn inference,鈥?in 2023 IEEE/ACM International | Conference on Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023, pp. 1鈥?0.
  L042: Systems, vol. 32, no. 9, pp. 2175鈥?187, 2021. | [14] K. Choi et al., 鈥淟egion: Tailoring grouped neural execution considering | heterogeneity on multiple edge devices,鈥?in IEEE Int. Conf. on Computer
  L054: South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2024. | [18] A. A. Abadi et al., 鈥淭ensorflow,鈥?https://www.tensorflow.org/, 2015. | [19] TensorFlow
  L055: [18] A. A. Abadi et al., 鈥淭ensorflow,鈥?https://www.tensorflow.org/, 2015. | [19] TensorFlow | Developers,
  L057: Developers, | TensorFlow | Guide:
  L059: Guide: | GPU | support
  L068: Available: | www.tensorflow.org/guide/gpu/#manual device placement | [20] Princeton
  L072: Computing, | TensorFlow | on
  L079: https://researchcomputing.princeton.edu/support/knowledge- | base/tensorflow, 2023. | [21] Y. G. Kim et al., 鈥淎utoscale: Energy efficiency optimization for stochas-
  L080: base/tensorflow, 2023. | [21] Y. G. Kim et al., 鈥淎utoscale: Energy efficiency optimization for stochas- | tic edge inference using reinforcement learning,鈥?Proc. of Int. Symp. on
  L086: Systems, 2024. | [23] NVIDIA, | 鈥淛etson
  L087: [23] NVIDIA, | 鈥淛etson | tx2
  L093: Available: | https://developer.nvidia.com/embedded/jetson-tx2 | [24] L. Zeng et al., 鈥淐oedge: Cooperative dnn inference with adaptive

========== Taufique 绛?- 2024 - Tango Low Latency Multi-DNN Inference on Heterogeneous Edge Platforms - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L033: We implemented the proposed Tango framework as a portable | middleware and deployed it on real hardware of the Jetson | TX edge platform. Our evaluation against relevant multi-DNN
  L034: middleware and deployed it on real hardware of the Jetson | TX edge platform. Our evaluation against relevant multi-DNN | scheduling strategies demonstrates 61% lower latency and 48.4%
  L036: scheduling strategies demonstrates 61% lower latency and 48.4% | lower energy consumption at a maximum accuracy loss of 1.59%. | Index Terms鈥擡dge AI, DNN inference, Heterogeneous systems
  L051: with other concurrently running DNNs. (i) Limited compute | capacity and energy budgets, and core-level heterogeneity | (e.g., asymmetric CPUs, GPUs, and custom accelerators) of
  L058: multi-DNN inference challenge. Minimizing DNN inference | latency within these constraints requires intelligent run-time | orchestration to schedule multi-DNN workloads efficiently.
  L065: global throughput; they achieve low latency inference for the | DNN mapped onto the GPU while compromising the latency | Fig. 1. Orchestrating concurrent DNNs with different scheduling strategies
  L071: gressive frequency scaling has only limited gains considering | the stringent power budgets of edge devices. Existing multi- | DNN inference techniques thus inevitably degrade the latency
  L090: platform. In this example, the First-come-first-serve (FCSFS) | scheduler maps the first arriving DNN-1 onto the GPU, and | the subsequent DNN-2 and DNN-3 onto the CPU clusters,
-- page 2 --
  L000: coordinated scheduler maps DNN-2 onto the GPU, DNN-3 | onto CPU cluster-1, and DNN-1 onto CPU cluster-2. This
  L002: onto CPU cluster-1, and DNN-1 onto CPU cluster-2. This | ensures low latency inference of DNN-2 onto the GPU; how- | ever DNN-1 and DNN-3 potentially fail to meet the latency
  L063: latency and maximize prediction accuracy | 鈥?Evaluation of the proposed solution on real hardware testbed | of Jetson TX embedded platform with 17 different combina-
  L064: 鈥?Evaluation of the proposed solution on real hardware testbed | of Jetson TX embedded platform with 17 different combina- | tions of DNN kernels, achieving upto 61% improved latency
  L066: tions of DNN kernels, achieving upto 61% improved latency | and 48% lower energy consumption | The paper is organized as follows: Section II provides
  L076: inferring multi-DNN workloads on heterogeneous platforms | with CPU and GPU support. We used Jetson TX board [7], | with a Pascal GPU, heterogeneous CPU clusters (quad-core
  L077: with CPU and GPU support. We used Jetson TX board [7], | with a Pascal GPU, heterogeneous CPU clusters (quad-core | ARM cluster and dual-core Denver cluster) as a baseline setup
  L082: Modern edge platforms, supported by heterogeneous CPU | and GPU clusters, exhibit diverse energy-latency charac- | teristics for multi-DNN workloads. Figure 2 shows the
  L085: performance-per-watt of inferring five different DNN kernels | on the Jetson TX. The convolution layers in DNNs have the | highest computation and energy requirement to perform nu-
  L086: on the Jetson TX. The convolution layers in DNNs have the | highest computation and energy requirement to perform nu- | merous Multiply鈥揂ccumulate operation (MAC) operations [8].
  L088: merous Multiply鈥揂ccumulate operation (MAC) operations [8]. | GPU and ARM clusters report low inference latency of the | DNNs because they allow parallelization of the convolution
  L092: latency because it is inherently designed to perform single- | threaded operations. GPU has the highest power consumption | but reports the highest performance-per-watt due to signifi-
  L094: but reports the highest performance-per-watt due to signifi- | cantly lower latency. The non-uniform energy-latency charac- | teristics of heterogeneous devices expose large design space
-- page 3 --
  L001: Fig. 3. Latency of DNN kernels in standalone vs multi-DNN workloads. | on the CPU and GPU clusters. For multi-DNN workloads, | we used the combinations of VGG-19 + MobileNetV2 1.0,
  L002: on the CPU and GPU clusters. For multi-DNN workloads, | we used the combinations of VGG-19 + MobileNetV2 1.0, | MobileNetV2 1.0 + ResNet-152, ResNet-152 + DenseNet-
  L003: we used the combinations of VGG-19 + MobileNetV2 1.0, | MobileNetV2 1.0 + ResNet-152, ResNet-152 + DenseNet- | 201, DenseNet-201 + EfficientNet-B4, and EfficientNet-B4 +
  L004: MobileNetV2 1.0 + ResNet-152, ResNet-152 + DenseNet- | 201, DenseNet-201 + EfficientNet-B4, and EfficientNet-B4 + | VGG-19 respectively. The standard Linux governors prioritize
  L005: 201, DenseNet-201 + EfficientNet-B4, and EfficientNet-B4 + | VGG-19 respectively. The standard Linux governors prioritize | GPU mapping of the DNN applications in the standalone mode
  L006: VGG-19 respectively. The standard Linux governors prioritize | GPU mapping of the DNN applications in the standalone mode | by default. As shown in Figure 3, inference latency of each
  L010: while the latency penalty is significantly higher when run on | the CPU clusters. For example, VGG-19 has an inference | latency of 0.4s when executed on GPU in standalone mode.
  L011: the CPU clusters. For example, VGG-19 has an inference | latency of 0.4s when executed on GPU in standalone mode. | However, it increases to 0.6s when MobileNetV2 concurrently
  L012: latency of 0.4s when executed on GPU in standalone mode. | However, it increases to 0.6s when MobileNetV2 concurrently | runs on the ARM cluster. Further, the inference latency of
  L014: runs on the ARM cluster. Further, the inference latency of | VGG-19 increases to 2.43s when executed on the ARM | cluster with MobileNetV2 concurrently running on the GPU.
  L015: VGG-19 increases to 2.43s when executed on the ARM | cluster with MobileNetV2 concurrently running on the GPU. | It should be noted that in Figure 3, the latency penalty is
  L021: requirements of a given inference request. For example, a | VGG-19 inference request with a target latency of 3s does not | get affected under the multi-DNN combination of VGG-19 +
  L022: VGG-19 inference request with a target latency of 3s does not | get affected under the multi-DNN combination of VGG-19 + | MobileNetV2. Conversely, the same inference request with a
  L023: get affected under the multi-DNN combination of VGG-19 + | MobileNetV2. Conversely, the same inference request with a | target latency of 0.5s violates the latency requirement under a
  L034: example of inferring two concurrent DNN kernels including | VGG and ResNet on Jetson TX where both the applications | require a minimum latency of 1s. With the placement config-
  L036: require a minimum latency of 1s. With the placement config- | uration Map1, VGG-19 is mapped on GPU, and Resnet152 is | mapped on the ARM-CPU cluster. Here, VGG-19 takes 0.6s
  L037: uration Map1, VGG-19 is mapped on GPU, and Resnet152 is | mapped on the ARM-CPU cluster. Here, VGG-19 takes 0.6s | per inference at 73% output accuracy, while ResNet-152 is
  L038: mapped on the ARM-CPU cluster. Here, VGG-19 takes 0.6s | per inference at 73% output accuracy, while ResNet-152 is | lagging the target with 1.8s latency at an output accuracy of
  L040: lagging the target with 1.8s latency at an output accuracy of | 76.6%. At Map2, the CPU and GPU mapping is switched | for VGG-19 and ResNet152. Now the VGG-19 takes 2.4s
  L041: 76.6%. At Map2, the CPU and GPU mapping is switched | for VGG-19 and ResNet152. Now the VGG-19 takes 2.4s | per inference, while the latency of ResNet152 is improved
  L042: for VGG-19 and ResNet152. Now the VGG-19 takes 2.4s | per inference, while the latency of ResNet152 is improved | to 0.59s per inference. In these mapping configurations, all
  L044: to 0.59s per inference. In these mapping configurations, all | CPUs and GPU are running at the highest frequencies, and | yet at least one DNN kernel is underperforming. The ex-
  L092: periment shows that both cluster mapping and DVFS have | computational and energy limitations, requiring an additional | control knob is required to achieve the target latency for a
  L095: multi-DNN workload. For Map1, we configure the accuracy of | VGG-19 by switching the kernel to VGG-16, achieving 0.65s | latency on the ARM-CPU cluster at an accuracy loss of 1.7%.
  L097: latency on the ARM-CPU cluster at an accuracy loss of 1.7%. | Similarly for Map2, we configure the accuracy of ResNet152 | by switching to ResNet50, achieving an inference latency of
-- page 4 --
  L005: pipelining and DVFS. The strategy performs static optimiza- | tion where the GPU kernels require 16-bit quantizations lead- | ing to scalability limitations. Table-I compares our proposed
  L011: for multi-DNN workloads on embedded platforms to minimize | inference latency while considering system energy minimiza- | tion and output accuracy improvement.
  L018: geneous Multi-Processing (HMP)-based edge devices, hosting | CPU and GPU clusters. Figure 5 shows an overview of the | proposed Tango framework. Tango comprises of (i) Applica-
  L057: automatically updates the corresponding voltage level. The | device supports run-time power monitoring through onboard | power sensors to analyze the impact of DVFS actuation on
  L058: device supports run-time power monitoring through onboard | power sensors to analyze the impact of DVFS actuation on | the energy budget of the device. For devices without power
  L059: power sensors to analyze the impact of DVFS actuation on | the energy budget of the device. For devices without power | sensors, external power sensing equipment can be used to
  L060: the energy budget of the device. For devices without power | sensors, external power sensing equipment can be used to | monitor run-time power consumption.
  L061: sensors, external power sensing equipment can be used to | monitor run-time power consumption. | Workloads. Tango framework supports concurrently running
  L069: perform cognitive tasks of classification, detection, tracking, | etc. In this work, we used (i) VGG, (ii) MobileNetV2, (iii) | ResNet, (iv) DenseNet, and (v) EfficientNet as the target
  L070: etc. In this work, we used (i) VGG, (ii) MobileNetV2, (iii) | ResNet, (iv) DenseNet, and (v) EfficientNet as the target | DNNs. The Application Module loads the drivers and kernels
-- page 5 --
  L013: Resource manager. The resource manager is implemented | with a feedback loop as a control system. It integrates an inter- | nal policy continuously executed with a predefined frequency
  L033: the total workload. The policy reads the cluster availability | to observe the current availability of CPU and GPU clusters | (Line 11). A cluster is considered unavailable for allocation if
  L092: workloads. We address the edge inference problem using | RL that is widely adopted for intelligent decision-making | in complex systems, using information collected over time.
-- page 6 --
  L008: as E = {E1, E2, .., En}, where Ei is a binary integer repre- | senting the busy status of the available CPU or GPU clusters. | DNN workloads are represented as W = {W1, W2, .., Wn},
  L052: executed different DNN kernels in each of their quantized | variants on the target platform [7] to collect latency, power | consumption, and accuracy. We used this data to train the RL
  L055: agent. The pre-trained RL is deployed in the Tango framework. | IV. EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION | A. Experimental Setup
  L056: IV. EXPERIMENTAL EVALUATION | A. Experimental Setup | Platform and middleware. For evaluation, we use Jetson TX
  L057: A. Experimental Setup | Platform and middleware. For evaluation, we use Jetson TX | [7] heterogeneous edge platform including Pascal GPU, quad-
  L058: Platform and middleware. For evaluation, we use Jetson TX | [7] heterogeneous edge platform including Pascal GPU, quad- | core ARM CPUs, and dual-core Denver CPUs. The device
  L060: core ARM CPUs, and dual-core Denver CPUs. The device | has onboard power sensors for collecting run-time power | consumption of CPU and GPU clusters. The device hosts
  L061: has onboard power sensors for collecting run-time power | consumption of CPU and GPU clusters. The device hosts | Linux-18.04 OS with Cuda support to enable GPU opera-
  L062: consumption of CPU and GPU clusters. The device hosts | Linux-18.04 OS with Cuda support to enable GPU opera- | tions. We have implemented the Tango framework (shown in
  L071: cluster and apply cluster-level DVFS settings at run-time. The | maximum operating frequency of the Pascal GPU is 1.12GHz, | the ARM cluster is 2GHz, and the Denver cluster is 2GHz,
  L076: we considered widely used image classification DNNs [14] | including, (i) VGG, (ii) MobileNetV2, (iii) ResNet, (iv) | DenseNet, and (v) EfficientNet. These models are highly
  L077: including, (i) VGG, (ii) MobileNetV2, (iii) ResNet, (iv) | DenseNet, and (v) EfficientNet. These models are highly | tunable with a wide energy-latency space, catering to diverse
  L078: DenseNet, and (v) EfficientNet. These models are highly | tunable with a wide energy-latency space, catering to diverse | real-world scenarios. All of these models are pre-trained on the
  L080: real-world scenarios. All of these models are pre-trained on the | ImageNet dataset [15]. We use the TensorFlow-GPU library | 305
-- page 7 --
  L000: Fig. 9. Comparison of (a). latency, (b). energy (c). accuracy of Tango against other strategies while running different combinations of 2 concurrent DNNs. | to infer the pre-trained models from the Keras application
  L007: Figure 8 shows the accuracy and latency trends of the base | DNNs and their lighter variants on all clusters of Jetson TX. | The accuracy-latency trend shows that typically the models are
  L009: The accuracy-latency trend shows that typically the models are | biased towards GPU. Secondly, the ARM cluster reports lesser | latency than Denver for most DNNs. For evaluation metrics,
  L010: biased towards GPU. Secondly, the ARM cluster reports lesser | latency than Denver for most DNNs. For evaluation metrics, | we use (i) latency as the time taken per inference, (ii) top-
  L014: labels and calculating the proportion of correctly classified | samples, and (iii) energy as the product of latency and the | average power consumption per inference.
  L015: samples, and (iii) energy as the product of latency and the | average power consumption per inference. | Comparison w.r.t. state-of-the-art approaches. We evaluated
  L027: uled the DNNs over ARM and Denver cluster. OmniBoost | [4] presents a DNN pipelining strategy over CPU and GPU | clusters using a Monte-Carlo tree-based throughput estimator.
  L031: the DAG-based DNN models and mapped them over the CPU | and GPU clusters. Finally, Band [2] minimized the latency by | jointly considering DNN pipelining and DVFS for CPUs, and
  L041: DNN requests to create concurrent workload scenarios. For | evaluation, we used a maximum of three concurrent DNNs for | the thermal safety of the evaluation platform while covering
  L042: evaluation, we used a maximum of three concurrent DNNs for | the thermal safety of the evaluation platform while covering | the majority of real-world scenarios. However, the Tango
  L047: Latency comparison for 2 concurrent applications. We eval- | uated the latency and energy of each strategy by concurrently | running two DNN applications in eight different combinations
  L055: the practical use of vision DNNs in edge and mobile platforms. | Similarly, Figure 9b shows the energy consumption of all | strategies across all workload combinations. The Ondemand
  L058: and SchedUtil governors randomly place one application on | GPU and the other on the ARM cluster as these clusters have | relatively high-performance capabilities. The greedy resource
  L060: relatively high-performance capabilities. The greedy resource | allocation approach of the governors leads to higher energy | consumption without meeting the required latency of the
-- page 8 --
  L000: Fig. 10. Comparison of (a). latency, (b). energy (c). accuracy of Tango against | other strategies while running different combinations of 3 concurrent DNNs.
  L004: latency against the other State-of-the-Art (SoA) approaches. | However, the strategy reports higher energy consumption in | multiple combinations due to high power consumption and
  L005: However, the strategy reports higher energy consumption in | multiple combinations due to high power consumption and | is still unable to achieve the target latency. Finally, Tango (i)
  L007: is still unable to achieve the target latency. Finally, Tango (i) | ensures coordinated inference by exploring the gain of placing | each application to different clusters, (ii) leverages latency
  L016: 84.59%, and 63.96 respectively. Similarly, Tango consumes | less energy consumption on average than other strategies | 47.89%, 23.62%, 25.49%, 36.77%, 84.31%, 77.55%, 64.54%,
  L021: Latency comparison for 3 concurrent applications. We | evaluated the latency and energy of each strategy for different | combinations of three concurrently running applications as
  L037: 9.82%, 52.17%, 75.48%, and 17.66% for each combination | respectively. Similarly, Tango improves energy consumption | by 8.44%, 59.46%, 85.21%, and 27.08% respectively. The
  L041: concurrently running applications is 1.69%. Overall, Tango | improves the latency and energy consumption by 61%, and | 48.4% for all the experiments at an accuracy loss of 1.9%.
  L048: for minimizing inference latency. We evaluated Tango on the | Jetson platform, achieving latency and energy improvements | of 61%, and 48.4% at a minimal accuracy loss of 1.59%
  L066: big. little multicore processors,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided | Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, vol. 39, no. 10, 2019. | [4] A. Karatzas et al., 鈥淥mniboost: Boosting throughput of heterogeneous
  L071: USA: ACM/IEEE, 2023. | [5] J. Kim et al., 鈥淓nergy-aware scenario-based mapping of deep learning | applications onto heterogeneous processors under real-time constraints,鈥?
  L074: IEEE Transactions on Computers, 2022. | [6] D. Kang et al., 鈥淛oint optimization of speed, accuracy, and energy for | embedded image recognition systems,鈥?in 2018 Design, Automation &
  L078: IEEE, 2018. | [7] NVIDIA, | 鈥淛etson
  L079: [7] NVIDIA, | 鈥淛etson | tx2
  L085: Available: | https://developer.nvidia.com/embedded/jetson-tx2 | [8] Z. Zhuoran et al., 鈥淒eepThings: Distributed adaptive deep learning
  L088: inference on resource-constrained IoT edge clusters,鈥?IEEE Trans. on | Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, 2018. | [9] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization
  L089: Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, 2018. | [9] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization | for power-efficient dnn inference,鈥?in 2023 IEEE/ACM International
  L090: [9] Y. Wu et al., 鈥淢oc: Multi-objective mobile cpu-gpu co-optimization | for power-efficient dnn inference,鈥?in 2023 IEEE/ACM International | Conference on Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023, pp. 1鈥?0.
  L101: coordinated | power/performance | management

========== Zhang 绛?- 2021 - DeepSlicing Collaborative and Adaptive CNN Inference With Low Latency - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L009: , Student Member, IEEE, and Sanglu Lu, Member, IEEE | Abstract鈥擳he booming of Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) has empowered lots of computer-vision applications. Due to its | stringent requirement for computing resources, substantial research has been conducted on how to optimize its deployment and
  L016: model and data, we also design an ef铿乧ient scheduler, Proportional Synchronized Scheduler (PSS), which achieves the trade-off | between computation and synchronization. Based on PyTorch, we have implemented DeepSlicing on the testbed with real-world edge | settings that consists of 8 heterogeneous Raspberry Pi鈥檚. The results indicate that DeepSlicing with PSS outperforms the existing
  L017: between computation and synchronization. Based on PyTorch, we have implemented DeepSlicing on the testbed with real-world edge | settings that consists of 8 heterogeneous Raspberry Pi鈥檚. The results indicate that DeepSlicing with PSS outperforms the existing | systems dramatically, e.g., the inference latency and memory footprint are reduced up to 5.79 and 14.72, respectively.
  L033: inference has a large demand in terms of the computing | resources. For instance, VGG-16 requires 15.5G MACs (mul- | tiply-add computations) to classify an image with 224  224
  L036: resolution [10]. On this account, conventional solutions per- | form inference on computationally powerful clouds to | reduce the latency. However, it is the network edge that the
  L060: and cloud so as to take advantage of both the network band- | width of edge and the computing power of cloud. Neverthe- | less, wide area network (WAN) transmission still exists and
  L078: Previous works [26], [27] only focus on chain-like CNNs, | e.g., YOLOv2 [6], VGG-16 [1]. In fact, there exist inception | and residual blocks in GoogLeNet [2] and ResNet [3], which
-- page 2 --
  L052: We have implemented DeepSlicing and deployed it over | 8 Raspberry Pi鈥檚. Empirical measurements show that, with | the optimization of the memory reclamation and communi-
-- page 3 --
  L077: inference time is reduced from 47.22 s to 30.93 s, 1.53 less. | Fig. 3. Roo铿俰ne model for Raspberry Pi4B and typical CNNs. | Fig. 4. Overlapped use of feature maps in CNNs.
-- page 5 --
  L071: have different depths but the same widths and heights, e.g., | Inception in GoogLeNet and Bottleneck in ResNet. As a con- | sequence, their input ranges are bijective to the correspond-
-- page 7 --
  L007: redundant computation while the latter suffers from fre- | quent synchronization. Empowered by the 铿乶e-grained | 铿俥xible scheduling mechanism of DeepSlicing, we devise
-- page 8 --
  L034: 6 | EVALUATION | We implement DeepSlicing in Python, and the deep learn-
  L036: We implement DeepSlicing in Python, and the deep learn- | ing framework used in DeepSlicing is PyTorch, one of the | most popular frameworks. In this section, we compare
  L042: Methodology | Metrics. Evaluation metrics are listed as follows. | Layer 铿乶ish time refers to the time from the start of the
  L065: exchanged between this worker and other workers. | Baselines. In evaluation, two typical state-of-the-art frame- | works are implemented and used as baselines: Deep-
  L076: data via a coordinator device. | Evaluation Setup. We implement DeepSlicing and PSS on | a real-world collaborative edge computing testbed that con-
  L077: Evaluation Setup. We implement DeepSlicing and PSS on | a real-world collaborative edge computing testbed that con- | sists of 8 Raspberry Pi鈥檚, 1 switch, and 1 router. Fig. 10
  L078: a real-world collaborative edge computing testbed that con- | sists of 8 Raspberry Pi鈥檚, 1 switch, and 1 router. Fig. 10 | shows the implemented hardware platform for DeepSlicing.
  L082: ties (Table 2). We use a router TP-LINK WDR7660 (2.4/5 | GHz WiFi, 1900 Mbps) and a switch TP-LINK SG1008M | (2000 Mbps) to represent wireless and wired connections,
  L083: GHz WiFi, 1900 Mbps) and a switch TP-LINK SG1008M | (2000 Mbps) to represent wireless and wired connections, | respectively. The router is used by default. We use an image
  L096: nience of comparison, the latency of single device is shown as | well, including 3B, 3Bp and 4B. We see, under both wireless | and wired networks and different worker number, that
  L098: and wired networks and different worker number, that | Fig. 10. Heterogeneous collaborative edge testbed. | TABLE 2
-- page 9 --
  L053: In this subsection, we compare the layer 铿乶ish times of | three frameworks on four typical CNNs (AlexNet, VGG19, | GoogLeNet, and ResNet50). Inference latency of a single
  L058: the advantage of DeepSlicing. When the CNN is simple (Alex- | Net and VGG19), MoDNN outperforms the single machine. | However, when the CNN is complex and deep (GoogLeNet
-- page 10 --
  L001: the contrary, DeepSlicing outperforms a single machine, | DeepThings, and MoDNN by up to 2.95 (VGG16), 1.39 | (ResNet50) and 5.20 (ResNet50), respectively. Whe-ther the
-- page 11 --
  L038: ignore the synchronization cost between devices. | Domain Speci铿乧 Hardware/Tools. The Intel OpenVino | modi铿乪s the model and accelerates the computation by
  L041: underlying libraries [31]. The Google TPU is designed to | provide enough computational power for deep learning [32]. | DeepSlicing is orthogonal to them and can run with these
-- page 12 --
  L016: Des. Implementation, 2018, pp. 269鈥?86. | [10] Z. Zhou, X. Chen, E. Li, L. Zeng, K. Luo, and J. Zhang, 鈥淓dge intel- | ligence: Paving the last mile of arti铿乧ial intelligence with edge
  L017: [10] Z. Zhou, X. Chen, E. Li, L. Zeng, K. Luo, and J. Zhang, 鈥淓dge intel- | ligence: Paving the last mile of arti铿乧ial intelligence with edge | computing,鈥?Proc. IEEE, vol. 107, no. 8, pp. 1738鈥?762, Aug. 2019.
  L038: vol. 12, no. 5, pp. 954鈥?66, 2020. | [18] Y. Kang et al., 鈥淣eurosurgeon: Collaborative intelligence between | the cloud and mobile edge,鈥?ACM SIGARCH Comput. Architecture
  L092: Comput. Syst., 2019, pp. 77鈥?0. | [31] Intel distribution of OpenVINO toolkit. [Online]. Available: | https://software.intel.com/content/www/us/en/develop/tools/
  L093: [31] Intel distribution of OpenVINO toolkit. [Online]. Available: | https://software.intel.com/content/www/us/en/develop/tools/ | openvino-toolkit.html
-- page 13 --
  L016: sity, Boca Raton, Florida. His current research interests include mobile | computing and wireless networks, routing protocols, cloud and green | computing, network trust and security, and social network applications.
  L049: research interests | include distributed computing, wireless networks, | and pervasive computing. She has published

========== Liu 绛?- 2024 - MoEI Mobility-Aware Edge Inference Based on Model Partition and Service Migration - IEEE Trans. on Mobile Comput..pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L013: Abstract鈥擠eep neural networks are the cornerstone of many | mobile intelligent systems, and their inference processes bring | about computation-intensive tasks. Device-edge cooperative infer-
  L059: Zhicheng Liu, Meng Tian, Xiaofei Wang, and Chao Qiu are with the Tianjin | Key Laboratory of Advanced Networking, College of Intelligence and Comput- | ing, Tianjin University, Tianjin 300350, China (e-mail: liuzhicheng@tju.edu.cn;
  L079: Illustration of edge collaborative inference with device mobility. | many mobile intelligent systems, encompassing areas such as | unmanned aerial vehicles, the Internet of healthcare things, and
  L081: unmanned aerial vehicles, the Internet of healthcare things, and | autonomous driving. The rapid growth of mobile intelligent ap- | plications results in a massive number of computation-intensive
-- page 2 --
  L021: viewpoint, recent studies advocate that learning-based frame- | works could empower mobile devices to perceive nonlinear | behavior patterns and take the decision-making process with
  L051: algorithm accordingly. Further, we design a deep reinforcement | learning algorithm that integrates Proximal Policy Optimization | (PPO), multi-head, and memory mechanisms to dynamically
  L104: By introducing DRL, Huang et al. design an online scheduling | scheme for intelligent mobile web [36]. Similarly, Xiao et al. | present a self-adaptive DNN con铿乬uration algorithm for smart
-- page 3 --
  L014: user | latency [15], energy consumption [38], migration cost [39], and | overall system utility [40]. Some solutions propose learning-
  L040: Each edge node is deployed with a base station to provide com- | puting resources through mobile wireless links. Additionally, | some edge nodes are directly connected by optical 铿乥er. The
-- page 4 --
  L036: C. Network Association and Transmission | The transmission process is divided into the wireless part and | the wired part. In terms of the wireless part, the node to which
  L037: The transmission process is divided into the wireless part and | the wired part. In terms of the wireless part, the node to which | mobiledevicenbelongsatslottisdenotedasbn(t).Withoutloss
  L048: Bn(t) = Bn鈥?t鈥? if bn(t) = bn鈥?t鈥?. The throughput rate of the | wireless part is denoted as Rn(t), which varies with wire- | less channel information such as belonging edge node, signal
  L060: is set to avoid too long transmission time. | The wireless transmission time can be described as | tn
  L069: A practical manner for service providers (e.g., Alicloud) to | manage computing resources (CPU, GPU, and memory) for AI | services is to divide the resources proportionally and package
-- page 8 --
  L003: Fig. 6. | Evaluation setup (a) uses Lumos5G dataset to simulate the mobility and transmission of mobile devices, (b) uses 3 types of embedding devices and 4 | types of Aliyun GPU service instances to simulate the computing process of mobile devices and edge nodes, (c) measures the inference time of 4 typical DNNs
  L004: Evaluation setup (a) uses Lumos5G dataset to simulate the mobility and transmission of mobile devices, (b) uses 3 types of embedding devices and 4 | types of Aliyun GPU service instances to simulate the computing process of mobile devices and edge nodes, (c) measures the inference time of 4 typical DNNs | on these entities, (d) considers compression performance under the condition of 2 inference datasets and 4 inference models, and (e) selects 20 partition points as
  L025: 系3) + T系2). | V. EVALUATION | A. Evaluation Setup
  L026: V. EVALUATION | A. Evaluation Setup | As shown in Fig. 6, we select a real-world 5G dataset to
  L047: m is | randomly assigned in [12x, 28x]. We de铿乶e an AliCloud GPU | service instance with the speci铿乧ation ecs.vgn7i-vws-m4.xlarge
  L050: as 1 unit of a service instance, which includes 4 vCPUs at | 2.9 GHz and 1/6 NVIDIA A10 GPU.1 We denote con铿乬ura- | tions with multiple resources {2x, 3x, 6x} as the corresponding
  L059: randomly assigned in {4x, 5x, 6x} and {1x, 2x}, respectively. | Mobile device capability setting: We select three NVIDIA | Jetson embedded devices with different computing capabilities
  L060: Mobile device capability setting: We select three NVIDIA | Jetson embedded devices with different computing capabilities | as mobile devices, including Nano with 0.47 TFLOPS, Xavier
  L061: Jetson embedded devices with different computing capabilities | as mobile devices, including Nano with 0.47 TFLOPS, Xavier | NX with 12 TOPS, and AGX Xavier with 32 TOPS.2 The default
  L062: as mobile devices, including Nano with 0.47 TFLOPS, Xavier | NX with 12 TOPS, and AGX Xavier with 32 TOPS.2 The default | number of mobile devices is set to 40, and their types are
  L080: compression settings to be measured. | B. Evaluation Baseline | The following 6 baselines are considered in the experimental
  L082: The following 6 baselines are considered in the experimental | evaluation. | r Local: All inference tasks are computed locally.
  L091: 1Alicloud: | https://www.alibabacloud.com/help/en/elastic-gpu-service/ | latest/vgpu-accelerated-instance-families
  L093: latest/vgpu-accelerated-instance-families | 2NVIDIA Jetson Modules: https://developer.nvidia.com/ embedded/jetson- | modules
-- page 9 --
  L026: mance and save the shortest average pipeline time among the last | 100 epochs for evaluation. For the proposed of铿俰ne algorithm, | we set iterMax = 100. For PPO and FL-PPO, we use the same
-- page 11 --
  L005: moving speed in walking scene, (c) the effect of throughput in driving scene, and (d) the effect of moving speed in driving scene, where blue lines with no mark in | (a)(c) represent the Cumulative Distribution Function (CDF) of wireless transmission throughput. | Fig. 12.
  L009: probability. | In terms of throughput, the wireless link quality of the walking | scene is signi铿乧antly better than that of the driving scene, which
-- page 12 --
  L024: In the future, we will consider the inference of铿俹ading at | the edge in more speci铿乧 intelligent applications. For example, | DNN-based mobile video analytics need to analyze and extract
  L034: REFERENCES | [1] G. Zhu et al., 鈥淧ushing AI to wireless network edge: An overview on | integrated sensing, communication, and computation towards 6G,鈥?Sci.
  L035: [1] G. Zhu et al., 鈥淧ushing AI to wireless network edge: An overview on | integrated sensing, communication, and computation towards 6G,鈥?Sci. | China Inf. Sci., vol. 66, no. 3, 2023, Art. no. 130301.
  L047: [5] F. Wang, J. Xu, X. Wang, and S. Cui, 鈥淛oint of铿俹ading and com- | puting optimization in wireless powered mobile-edge computing sys- | tems,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wirel. Commun., vol. 17, no. 3, pp. 1784鈥?797,
  L050: Mar. 2018. | [6] Z.Huangetal.,鈥淓nablinglowlatencyedgeintelligencebasedonmulti-exit | dnns in the wild,鈥?in Proc. IEEE 41st Int. Conf. Distrib. Comput. Syst.,
  L073: [10] P. Wang, T. Ouyang, G. Liao, J. Gong, S. Yu, and X. Chen, 鈥淓dge | intelligence in motion: Mobility-aware dynamic dnn inference service | migration with downtime in mobile edge computing,鈥?J. Syst. Archit.,
  L105: [20] J. Li, W. Liang, Y. Li, Z. Xu, X. Jia, and S. Guo, 鈥淭hroughput maximization | of delay-aware DNN inference in edge computing by exploring DNN | model partitioning and inference parallelism,鈥?IEEE Trans. Mob. Comput.,
  L123: [25] F. Dong et al., 鈥淢ulti-exit DNN inference acceleration based on multi- | dimensional optimization for edge intelligence,鈥?IEEE Trans. Mob. Com- | put., vol. 22, no. 9, pp. 5389鈥?405, Sep. 2023.
-- page 13 --
  L024: pp. 7038鈥?047, Oct. 2022. | [38] X. Zhou, S. Ge, T. Qiu, K. Li, and M. Atiquzzaman, 鈥淓nergy-ef铿乧ient | service migration for multi-user heterogeneous dense cellular networks,鈥?
  L036: Trans. Serv. Comput., vol. 15, no. 2, pp. 669鈥?83, Mar./Apr. 2022. | [42] X. Li, S. Chen, Y. Zhou, J. Chen, and G. Feng, 鈥淚ntelligent service | migration based on hidden state inference for mobile edge computing,鈥?
  L063: policy optimization algorithms,鈥?2017, arXiv: 1707.06347. | [51] Z. Ning et al., 鈥淒eep reinforcement learning for intelligent Internet of | Vehicles: An energy-ef铿乧ient computational of铿俹ading scheme,鈥?IEEE
  L064: [51] Z. Ning et al., 鈥淒eep reinforcement learning for intelligent Internet of | Vehicles: An energy-ef铿乧ient computational of铿俹ading scheme,鈥?IEEE | Trans. Cogn. Commun. Netw., vol. 5, no. 4, pp. 1060鈥?072, Dec. 2019.
  L081: toward the PhD degree in computer science with | the college of intelligence and computing, Tianjin | University, China. He is also a visiting student with
  L090: He is currently working toward the MS degree in | computer science with the college of intelligence | and computing, Tianjin University, Tianjin, China.
  L092: and computing, Tianjin University, Tianjin, China. | His research interests include edge intelligence and | reinforcement learning.
  L120: 2014 to 2016. He is currently a professor with the | College of Intelligence and Computing, Tianjin Uni- | versity, Tianjin, China. Focusing on the research of
  L122: versity, Tianjin, China. Focusing on the research of | edge computing, edge intelligence, and edge systems, | he has published more than 150 technical papers in
  L126: Cloud Computing, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, IEEE Transactions | on Wireless Communications, IoTJ, IEEE Communications Surveys and Tutori- | als, IEEE Transactions on Multimedia, INFOCOM, ICDCS, and so on. In 2017,
-- page 14 --
  L008: She is currently a lecturer with the School of Com- | puterScienceandTechnology,CollegeofIntelligence | and Computing, Tianjin University. From 2017 to
  L012: Canada, as a Visiting Scholar. Her current research | interests include machine learning, computing power | networking, and blockchain.
  L016: ate degree in computer science and technology from | Tianjin University majoring in 2021 and the doctorate | degree in engineering. From 2018 to 2019, he visited

========== Li 绛?- 2020 - Edge AI On-Demand Accelerating Deep Neural Network Inference via Edge Computing - IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun..pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L000: IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | 447
  L009: , Member, IEEE | Abstract鈥擜s a key technology of enabling Arti铿乧ial Intel- | ligence (AI) applications in 5G era, Deep Neural Networks
  L022: adaptively partitions computation between device and edge for | purpose of coordinating the powerful cloud resource and the | proximal edge resource for real-time DNN inference; (2) DNN
  L036: con铿乬uration. We implement Edgent prototype based on the | Raspberry Pi and the desktop PC and the extensive experimental | evaluations demonstrate Edgent鈥檚 effectiveness in enabling on-
  L037: Raspberry Pi and the desktop PC and the extensive experimental | evaluations demonstrate Edgent鈥檚 effectiveness in enabling on- | demand low-latency edge intelligence.
  L038: evaluations demonstrate Edgent鈥檚 effectiveness in enabling on- | demand low-latency edge intelligence. | Index Terms鈥擡dge intelligence, edge computing, deep learn-
  L039: demand low-latency edge intelligence. | Index Terms鈥擡dge intelligence, edge computing, deep learn- | ing, computation of铿俹ading.
  L063: A | S THE backbone technology supporting modern intelli- | gent mobile applications, Deep Neural Networks (DNNs)
  L075: In response to the excessive resource demand of DNNs, | traditional wisdom resorts to the powerful cloud datacenter | for intensive DNN computation. In this case, the input data
  L084: network, which may potentially result in intolerable latency | and extravagant energy. To alleviate this problem, we exploit | the emerging edge computing paradigm. The principal idea
  L091: intensive and latency-critical DNN-based applications to be | executed in a real-time responsive manner (i.e., edge intelli- | gence) [15]. By leveraging edge computing, we can design
  L095: supporting real-time edge AI applications. | While recognizing the bene铿乼s of edge intelligence, our | empirical study reveals that the performance of edge-based
  L099: width between the edge server and the mobile device. Specif- | ically, as the bandwidth drops from 1Mbps to 50kbps, the | edge-based DNN inference latency increases from 0.123s to
  L106: for some mission-critical DNN-based applications such as | intelligent security and industrial robotics [16]. | 1536-1276 漏 2019 IEEE. Personal use is permitted, but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission.
-- page 2 --
  L001: 448 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | On this issue, in this paper, we exploit the edge computing
  L005: framework via device-edge synergy. Towards low-latency | edge intelligence,1 Edgent pursues two design knobs. The | 铿乺st is DNN partitioning, which adaptively partitions DNN
  L013: formance is still restrained by the rest of the model run- | ning on mobile devices. Therefore, Edgent further integrate | the second knob, DNN right-sizing, which accelerates DNN
  L044: without violating the application responsiveness requirement. | The prototype implementation and extensive evaluations based | on the Raspberry Pi and the desktop PC demonstrate Edgent鈥檚
  L045: The prototype implementation and extensive evaluations based | on the Raspberry Pi and the desktop PC demonstrate Edgent鈥檚 | effectiveness in enabling on-demand low-latency edge intelli-
  L046: on the Raspberry Pi and the desktop PC demonstrate Edgent鈥檚 | effectiveness in enabling on-demand low-latency edge intelli- | gence.
  L062: 1As an initial study, in this work, we focus on the problem of execution | latency optimization. Energy ef铿乧iency will be considered in future studies. | environment), we specialize the work铿俹w design for
  L066: 鈥?We implement and experiment Edgent prototype with | a Raspberry Pi and a desktop PC. The evaluation results | based on the real-world network trace dataset demonstrate
  L077: Discussions on the topic of mobile DNN computation have | recently obtained growing attention. By hosting arti铿乧ial intel- | ligence on mobile devices, mobile DNN computation deploys
  L085: the DNN computation on edge devices. | Towards low-latency and energy-ef铿乧ient mobile DNN com- | putation, there are mainly three ways in the literature: runtime
-- page 3 --
  L010: require different execution deadlines under different scenar- | ios. Secondly, Edgent integrates both DNN partitioning and | DNN right-sizing to maximize the inference accuracy while
  L022: the inference before the application deadline. | Therefore, we propose to integrate these two approaches to | expand the design space. The integration of model partitioning
  L023: Therefore, we propose to integrate these two approaches to | expand the design space. The integration of model partitioning | and model right-sizing is not a one-step effort, and we need to
  L050: DNN has served as the core technology for a wide range | of intelligent applications across Computer Vision (CV) [2] | and Natural Language Processing (NLP) [4]. Fig. 1 shows
  L069: inference rather than DNN training since the training process | is generally delay-tolerant and often done of铿俰ne on powerful | cloud datacenters.
  L077: to meet real-time applications latency requirements [10]. For | illustration, we employ a Raspberry Pi and a desktop PC | to emulate the mobile device and edge server respectively,
  L086: constrained mobile device. As a contrast, the edge server | only spends 0.123s for inference under a 1Mbps bandwidth. | However, as the bandwidth drops, the execution latency of
-- page 4 --
  L001: 450 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | Fig. 3.
  L003: Fig. 3. | AlexNet layer-wise runtime and output data size on Raspberry Pi. | bandwidth resources in practice (e.g., due to network resource
  L010: C. DNN Partitioning and Right-Sizing towards Edge | Intelligence | DNN Partitioning: To better understand the performance
  L013: bottleneck of DNN inference, in Fig. 3 we re铿乶e the layer- | wise execution latency (on Raspberry Pi) and the intermediate | output data size per layer. Seen from Fig. 3, the latency
-- page 6 --
  L001: 452 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | latency for transferring input data and intermediate execution
-- page 7 --
  L076: co-inference stage. | V. PERFORMANCE EVALUATION | In this section, we present our implementation of Edgent
  L078: In this section, we present our implementation of Edgent | and the evaluation results. | A. Experimental Setup
  L079: and the evaluation results. | A. Experimental Setup | We implement a prototype based on the Raspberry Pi and
  L080: A. Experimental Setup | We implement a prototype based on the Raspberry Pi and | the desktop PC to demonstrate the feasibility and ef铿乧iency of
  L082: the desktop PC to demonstrate the feasibility and ef铿乧iency of | Edgent. Equipped with a quad-core 3.40 GHz Intel processor | and 8 GB RAM, a desktop PC is served as the edge server.
  L085: Equipped with a quad-core 1.2 GHz ARM processor and 1 GB | RAM, a Raspberry Pi 3 is used to act as a mobile device. | To set up a static bandwidth environment, we use the
  L093: provided by Oboe [43] to generate 428 bandwidth states range | from 0Mbps to 6Mbps. | To obtain the branchy DNN, we employ BranchyNet [40]
  L109: both the edge server and the mobile device for performance | evaluation. Speci铿乧ally, due to the high-impact characteristics | of the latency requirement and the available bandwidth during
  L116: the latency requirement at 1000ms and setting the bandwidth | from 50kbps to 1.5Mbps. Fig. 8(a) shows the optimal co- | inference plan (i.e., the selection of partition point and exit
-- page 8 --
  L001: 454 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | Fig. 8.
  L070: state 铿倁ctuation, from which we obtain 428 bandwidth states | range from 0Mbps to 6Mbps. According to the Algorithm 2, | through the exhaustive search, we 铿乬ure out the optimal
  L075: For online change point detection, we use the existing | implementation [48] and integrate it with the Runtime Opti- | mizer. We use the Belgium 4G/LTE bandwidth logs dataset
-- page 9 --
  L006: transportation: on foot, bicycle, bus, train or car. Additionally, | Since that most of the bandwidth logs are over 6Mbps and in | some cases even up to 95Mbps, to adjust the edge computing
  L007: Since that most of the bandwidth logs are over 6Mbps and in | some cases even up to 95Mbps, to adjust the edge computing | scenario, in our experiment, we scale down the bandwidth of
  L009: scenario, in our experiment, we scale down the bandwidth of | the logs and limit it in a range from 0Mbps to 10Mbps. | In this experiment Edgent runs in a dynamic bandwidth
  L068: inference framework with device-edge collaboration. Enabling | low-latency edge intelligence, Edgent introduces two design | knobs to optimize the DNN inference latency: DNN partition-
  L075: environments, respectively. Our prototype implementation and | the experimental evaluation on Raspberry Pi shows the feasi- | bility and effectiveness of Edgent towards low-latency edge
  L077: bility and effectiveness of Edgent towards low-latency edge | intelligence. For the future work, our proposed framework | can be further combined with existing model compression
  L083: We hope to stimulate more discussion and efforts in the society | and fully realize the vision of edge intelligence. | Authorized licensed use limited to: Huazhong University of Science and Technology. Downloaded on May 16,2025 at 02:19:08 UTC from IEEE Xplore.  Restrictions apply.
-- page 10 --
  L001: 456 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 19, NO. 1, JANUARY 2020 | REFERENCES
  L003: REFERENCES | [1] E. Li, Z. Zhou, and X. Chen, 鈥淓dge intelligence: On-demand deep learn- | ing model co-inference with device-edge synergy,鈥?in Proc. Workshop
  L036: [10] X. Chen, Q. Shi, L. Yang, and J. Xu, 鈥淭hriftyedge: Resource-ef铿乧ient | edge computing for intelligent IoT applications,鈥?IEEE Netw., vol. 32, | no. 1, pp. 61鈥?5, Jan./Feb. 2018.
  L039: [11] Y. Yang, K. Wang, G. Zhang, X. Chen, X. Luo, and M. Zhou, | 鈥淢EETS: Maximal energy ef铿乧ient task scheduling in homogeneous | fog networks,鈥?IEEE Internet Things J., vol. 5, no. 5, pp. 4076鈥?087,
  L064: Zhang, | 鈥淓dge intelligence: | Paving the last mile of arti铿乧ial intelligence
  L065: 鈥淓dge intelligence: | Paving the last mile of arti铿乧ial intelligence | with edge computing,鈥?2019, arXiv:1905.10083. [Online]. Available:
  L071: [17] Q. Cao, N. Balasubramanian, and A. Balasubramanian, 鈥淢obiRNN: | Ef铿乧ient recurrent neural network execution on mobile GPU,鈥?in Proc. | 1st Int. Workshop Deep Learn. Mobile Syst. Appl., 2017, pp. 1鈥?.
  L084: (UBICOMP), Sep. 2015, pp. 283鈥?94. | [21] A. G. Howard et al., 鈥淢obileNets: Ef铿乧ient convolutional neural | networks for mobile vision applications,鈥?2017, arXiv:1704.04861.
  L092: [23] Y.-D. Kim, E. Park, S. Yoo, T. Choi, L. Yang, and D. Shin, 鈥淐om- | pression of deep convolutional neural networks for fast and low power | mobile applications,鈥?2015, arXiv:1511.06530. [Online]. Available:
  L101: search by network transformation,鈥?in Proc. 32nd AAAI Conf. Artif. | Intell., 2018, pp. 2787鈥?794. | [26] C. Liu et al., 鈥淧rogressive neural architecture search,鈥?in Proc. Eur. Conf.
  L130: Program. Gate Arrays, 2017, pp. 65鈥?4. | [30] B. Reagen et al., 鈥淢inerva: Enabling low-power, highly-accurate deep | neural network accelerators,鈥?in Proc. ACM/IEEE 43rd Annu. Int. Symp.
  L140: [33] B. Islam, Y. Luo, and S. Nirjon, 鈥淶ygarde: Time-sensitive on- | device deep intelligence on intermittently-powered systems,鈥?2019, | arXiv:1905.03854.
  L146: 03854 | [34] Y. Kang et al., 鈥淣eurosurgeon: Collaborative intelligence between the | cloud and mobile edge,鈥?ACM SIGARCH Comput. Archit. News, vol. 45,
  L150: [35] A. E. Eshratifar, M. S. Abrishami, and M. Pedram, 鈥淛ointDNN: | An ef铿乧ient training and inference engine for intelligent mobile cloud | computing services,鈥?2018, arXiv:1801.08618. [Online]. Available:
  L164: [39] J. Zhou, Y. Wang, K. Ota, and M. Dong, 鈥淎AIoT: Accelerating arti铿乧ial | intelligence in IoT systems,鈥?IEEE Wireless Commun. Lett., vol. 8, no. 3, | pp. 825鈥?28, Jun. 2019.
  L205: http:// | manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/trusty/man8/wondershaper.8.html | [46] J. van der Hooft et al., 鈥淗TTP/2-based adaptive streaming of HEVC
-- page 11 --
  L009: sen University, Guangzhou. His research interests | include mobile deep computing, edge intelligence, | and deep learning.
  L031: of the Best Paper Award of the IEEE UIC 2018. He is the General Co- | Chair of the 2018 International Workshop on Intelligent Cloud Computing | and Networking (ICCN).
  L050: Professional Best Paper Award, the Honorable Mention Award of the 2010 | IEEE International Conference on Intelligence and Security Informatics (ISI), | the Best Paper Runner-up Award of the 2014 IEEE International Conference
