NOT FOUND: C:\Users\victor\Nutstore\1\zotero\鍗槦缃戠粶\妯″瀷鍒嗗壊\R??i?ka 绛?- 2023 - Fast Model Inference and Training On-Board of Satellites - .pdf

========== Plumridge 绛?- 2025 - Rapid Distributed Fine-tuning of a Segmentation Model Onboard Satellites - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L036: iX10-100 satellite hardware. We demonstrate the segmentation | of water bodies from Sentinel-2 satellite imagery and integrate | MobileSAM with PASEOS, an open-source Python module that
  L038: MobileSAM with PASEOS, an open-source Python module that | simulates satellite operations. This integration allows us to eval- | uate MobileSAM鈥檚 performance under simulated conditions of a
-- page 2 --
  L018: remote sensing applications. Despite some promising results, | the authors recommend exploring fine-tuning to improve per- | formance with coarser resolution EO data, which we do in
  L032: constraints than on Earth. In orbit, spacecraft need to regulate | their temperature, manage power efficiently, and deal with | constantly changing availability and limited bandwidth of
  L038: source Python module PASEOS [17]. PASEOS offers utilities | for monitoring onboard and operational constraints, including | thermal, power, bandwidth and communication constraints. In
  L039: for monitoring onboard and operational constraints, including | thermal, power, bandwidth and communication constraints. In | this work, we use PASEOS to observe power and temper-
  L040: thermal, power, bandwidth and communication constraints. In | this work, we use PASEOS to observe power and temper- | ature trends during training of MobileSAM onboard multiple
  L052: goal of rapid response. | 3) We integrate MobileSAM with the PASEOS simulation | software, developing a code base that enables easy
  L064: Our methodology consists of: 1) data acquisition and pre- | processing, 2) integration of MobileSAM with PASEOS, 3) | model deployment and bench-marking on satellite hardware.
-- page 3 --
  L036: equipped with a diverse set of compute, including CPU, an | onboard GPU and a VPU, to enable in-orbit processing of | demanding space applications [20].
  L043: Fig. 2. MobileSAM model architecture. Image adapted from [16]. | the hardware and the battery power is essential to determine | the feasibility of running processes onboard. Additionally, in
  L048: ground stations that they communicate with is critical. The | PASEOS simulation software enables our evaluation of these | aspects. More details about the software can be found in the
  L052: We configure simulation scenarios as described in Table. I. | In particular, we model the power consumption and thermal | impact on satellites when performing the following operations:
-- page 4 --
  L012: from the disaster site. Further IoU measurements on the full | evaluation set of 167 tiles are displayed in Fig. 5. | The time required for model fine-tuning is benchmarked
  L016: satellite and ground truth tile pairs takes 2.01 seconds on | the Unibap GPU. Over a simulation period of 24-hours, | the GPU can therefore fine-tune on 42,985 batches of data
  L017: the Unibap GPU. Over a simulation period of 24-hours, | the GPU can therefore fine-tune on 42,985 batches of data | corresponding to 2,687 tile pairs. After benchmarking on the
  L020: Unibap device, full simulations and model fine-tuning are | conducted on NVIDIA A100-SXM4-40GB GPUs provided | by the JASMIN data analysis facility [27]. The GPU cluster
  L021: conducted on NVIDIA A100-SXM4-40GB GPUs provided | by the JASMIN data analysis facility [27]. The GPU cluster | consists of 4 nodes each containing 4 GPUs, enabling our
  L055: Fig. 6. | Satellite conditions during model training and evaluation. Model | exchanges are shown for just a one hour period for demonstration purposes.
-- page 5 --
  L055: small dataset. We also observe that, when accounting for op- | erational constraints such as temperature and power, Mobile- | SAM can effectively be fine-tuned onboard satellite hardware,
-- page 6 --
  L004: Furthermore, overfitting risks associated with small, domain- | specific datasets necessitate careful monitoring. Future work | will consider self-supervised learning approaches to mitigate
  L027: the UKRI Centre for Doctoral Training in the Application | of Artificial Intelligence to the study of Environmental Risks | (AI4ER), led by the University of Cambridge and the British
  L043: [2] G. Furano, G. Meoni, A. Dunne, D. Moloney, V. Ferlet-Cavrois, A. | Tavoularis, et al., 鈥漈owards the use of artificial intelligence on the edge | in space systems: Challenges and opportunities,鈥?IEEE Aerospace and

========== Guan 绛?- 2024 - Collaborative Inference in DNN-Based Satellite Systems with Dynamic Task Streams - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L007: {mr guanjl;qyzhang;sgwang}@bupt.edu.cn;{imurturi;pdonta;dustdar}@dsg.tuwien.ac.at | Abstract鈥擜s a driving force in the advancement of intel- | ligent in-orbit applications, DNN models have been gradually
  L009: ligent in-orbit applications, DNN models have been gradually | integrated into satellites, producing daily latency-constraint and | computation-intensive tasks. However, the substantial computa-
  L022: accuracy by dynamically choosing early-exit and partition points. | Simulation evaluations show that our proposed algorithm signif- | icantly outperforms baseline algorithms across the task stream
  L045: where the data is generated [5]. However, the majority of | LEO satellites are equipped with limited computing power | and small physical size, which pose challenges in handling
  L061: It is reported that even a free-space laser link achieves up | to 1.8 Gbps data rate [7]. When faced with extensive and | diverse computational demands, it is necessary to collaborate
-- page 2 --
  L020: cient solution to the formulated problem. | 鈥?Simulation evaluations show that our proposed algorithm | significantly outperforms the baseline algorithms across
  L031: at enhancing satellite data transmission efficiency. Cheng et | al. [10] proposed an integrated satellite-ground computing | architecture that utilizes satellites to enable access to cloud
  L050: computing schemes, the entire inference process is executed | on satellites. The limited computing resources and low energy | acquisition capabilities of this approach also place a heavy
-- page 3 --
  L150: (3) | where Pt denotes the transmit power, Gt denotes the receive | gain, Gr denotes the transmit gain, f denotes the carrier
-- page 5 --
  L063: that the current task should be associated with. | V. SIMULATION EVALUATIONS | In this section, we evaluate the performance of our proposed
  L086: corresponding inference accuracy of 5 EE points is [0, 0.527, | 0.623, 0.697, 0.743]. In the evaluation, task generation follows | Bernoulli distribution with p = 0.1, ensuring that at most
-- page 6 --
  L103: VI. CONCLUSION | The paper proposes a framework for collaborative intelligent | inference for various satellite inference tasks based on multi-
  L109: problem theoretically and design a task gain-aware algorithm | to solve this issue. Simulation evaluations show that the | proposed algorithm outperforms that of baseline algorithms,
  L176: [14] Y. Kang, J. Hauswald, C. Gao, A. Rovinski, T. Mudge, J. Mars, and | L. Tang, 鈥淣eurosurgeon: Collaborative intelligence between the cloud | and mobile edge,鈥?ACM SIGARCH Computer Architecture News, vol. 45,
  L180: [15] A. E. Eshratifar, M. S. Abrishami, and M. Pedram, 鈥淛ointdnn: An | efficient training and inference engine for intelligent mobile cloud | computing services,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing, vol. 20,
  L189: deep neural network inference via edge computing,鈥?IEEE Transactions | on Wireless Communications, vol. 19, no. 1, pp. 447鈥?57, 2019. | [18] J. Song, Z. Liu, X. Wang, C. Qiu, and X. Chen, 鈥淎daptive and

========== Zhang 绛?- 2025 - Communication-Efficient Distributed On-Device LLM Inference Over Wireless Networks - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L002: Communication-Efficient Distributed On-Device | LLM Inference Over Wireless Networks | Kai Zhang, Hengtao He, Member, IEEE, Shenghui Song, Senior Member, IEEE,
  L018: air computation (AirComp) approach that harnesses the ana- | log superposition property of wireless multiple-access channels | to perform fast all-reduce steps. To utilize the heterogeneous
  L035: The advent of large language models (LLMs) has marked a | significant breakthrough in artifical intelligence (AI), demon- | strating superior performance and adaptability in a wide range
  L038: of applications, such as natural language processing [2]鈥揫4], | embodied intelligence [5]鈥揫7], and wireless communications | [8]鈥揫10]. The efficacy of LLMs is primarily attributed to
  L076: advancements in communication technologies, such as the 5G | and future 6G wireless networks, enhance the feasibility of | distributed LLM inference for real-time applications [15], [16].
  L091: based algorithm to find the optimal trade-off between inference | delay and energy consumption. In [19], He et al. developed | an active inference method to address the joint task offloading
  L098: device and cloud server to reduce the communication overhead | under varying wireless network conditions. Furthermore, task- | oriented communications have been utilized to optimize end-
  L107: substantial challenges in terms of feasibility and scalability | due to its reliance on a powerful centralized cloud server | with high computational capability. Moreover, prior works
  L111: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 2 --
  L039: Training Latency and | Energy Consumption | 脳
  L093: across multiple edge devices. It not only eliminates the reliance | on a powerful central server but also enables concurrent | processing of model segments across devices, significantly
  L100: communication-intensive all-reduce steps can cause substantial | latency in practical wireless networks and hinder real-time | inference, necessitating efficient communication strategies to
  L107: (AirComp) approach to facilitate fast all-reduce operations. | AirComp leverages the superposition property of wireless | multiple-access channels, allowing simultaneous transmissions
  L121: ence system, however, is heavily influenced by the com- | munication efficiency, particularly given the limited energy | resources of edge devices. Thus, to improve the inference
  L127: joint optimization is crucial considering the heterogeneous | computation capabilities of edge devices and varying wireless | channel conditions. Optimal model assignment ensures that
  L131: its computational capability (e.g., memory size and compute | power), while transceiver optimization minimizes the commu- | nication distortions during the AirComp process. To simplify
  L148: cessive convex approximation (SCA). We note that although | existing wireless optimization techniques (e.g., SDR and SCA | algorithms) have been well studied, their tailored applica-
  L157: tation, handling of heterogeneous device capabilities, multi- | antenna AirComp beamforming designs, and stringent energy | constraints.
  L161: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 3 --
  L070: communication-efficient AirComp all-reduce approach by ex- | ploiting the signal superposition property of wireless multiple- | access channels.
  L138: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 4 --
  L015: infrastructure. By equipping cluster nodes with dedicated wire- | less interfaces (e.g., WiFi or private 5G networks), AirComp | enables low-latency inference and reduces communication
  L021: or localized edge servers (e.g., home gateway servers or on- | premises GPU nodes). Operating within a secure localized | environment, these devices can safely share raw input data
  L028: edge environments by leveraging ubiquitous short-range wire- | less technologies (e.g., WiFi) that have been implemented on | personal devices such as smartphones and home servers. This
  L150: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 5 --
  L103: requires frequent all-reduce operations, which cause signifi- | cant communication overhead in practical wireless networks. | To address this issue, we propose a communication-efficient
  L107: tributed data efficiently by leveraging the signal superposi- | tion property of wireless multiple-access channels, allowing | simultaneous transmissions to compute nomographic functions
  L124: aggregation at the receiver. | We consider a wireless network consisting of an edge server | with Nr antennas and N single-antenna edge devices. We
  L134: Zn, which has a complete dimensionality of L0. To reduce | transmission power, the transmitted symbols are normalized to | have zero mean and unit variance, i.e., E[鈭n鈭?] = 1, where
  L151: where hn 鈭圕Nr脳1 denotes the uplink channel from device n | to the server, bn is the transmit power of device n, and n 鈭?| CN
  L158: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 6 --
  L001: 6 | with 蟽2 being the noise power. In the single-antenna setting, | each device employs only a scalar transmit-power coefficient
  L002: with 蟽2 being the noise power. In the single-antenna setting, | each device employs only a scalar transmit-power coefficient | bn (instead of a beamforming vector) to scale its transmitted
  L030: Edge devices involved in inference tasks typically have | limited energy supply. Thus, we assume that for each device | n, the energy consumption for both the forward computation
  L031: limited energy supply. Thus, we assume that for each device | n, the energy consumption for both the forward computation | of each LLM layer and the transmission of the intermediate
  L033: of each LLM layer and the transmission of the intermediate | output cannot exceed the maximum power budget P max | n
  L036: . To | model the computation energy consumption, we first introduce | a model assignment vector m = [m1, . . . , mN] with its entry
  L039: mn 鈭圼0, 1] representing the proportion of model allocated to | device n. Consequently, the computation energy consumption | for device n is given by enmnstot, where en denotes the
  L041: for device n is given by enmnstot, where en denotes the | device-specific energy coefficient that reflects the energy cost | associated with accessing and processing each weight during
  L044: computation, and stot is the number of parameters (weights) | for each layer. The communication energy consumption of | device n can be derived as L0鈭n鈭?. Accordingly, the power
  L045: for each layer. The communication energy consumption of | device n can be derived as L0鈭n鈭?. Accordingly, the power | constraint is given by
  L057: portion of the model based on its computational capability | (e.g., memory size and compute power). Meanwhile, efficient | transceiver optimization can reduce signal misalignment error
  L063: that aims to minimize the average MSE, subject to the per- | device power constraints. Importantly, the transceiver design | can adapt dynamically to instantaneous CSI. In contrast,
  L100: prior knowledge of channel statistics. | 鈥?Interdependence of Timescales: The per-device power | constraints link the short-term transceiver variables with
  L152: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 7 --
  L001: 7 | wireless systems. To address these challenges, we propose a | stochastic SCA algorithm that operates without requiring prior
  L024: satisfies gHg = 1, and consequently a = 鈭毼眊 where 伪 is | optimized to satisfy the power constraints of edge devices. | By applying Lemma 1, problem Ps can be reformulated as
  L164: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 8 --
  L001: 8 | the recursive convex approximation of the power constraint | function f1(m) is given by
  L155: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 9 --
  L111: single-antenna case, all devices simultaneously upload their | intermediate layer outputs through wireless multiple-access | channels. Let zn = [zn,1, . . . , zn,L]T denote the per-round
  L162: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 10 --
  L217: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 11 --
  L012: 1) LLM Inference Model Setting: All simulations are per- | formed on a desktop server equipped with Nvidia GeForce | RTX 4070Ti GPU and Intel Core i9 CPU, using PyTorch
  L013: formed on a desktop server equipped with Nvidia GeForce | RTX 4070Ti GPU and Intel Core i9 CPU, using PyTorch | 2.0 with CUDA 11.7. We set up N virtual machines (VMs)
  L018: space, ensuring efficient utilization of computational resources | and optimized parallel processing. For evaluation, we utilize | the LLaMA2 [55] and LLaMA3 [11] models due to their
  L023: widely used in the field of LLM inference for benchmark- | ing and evaluation purposes. We have released our imple- | mentation on GitHub: https://github.com/zklasd24/distributed
  L054: Gaussian random variables with non-zero mean 碌 = 1 and | variance 蟽2 = 1. Moreover, the maximum power budget is | set as P max
  L075: network scenarios. | C. Performance Evaluation | In this subsection, we compare the performance of the
  L105: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 12 --
  L044: communication strategies. Specifically, by exploiting analog | signal superposition inherent in wireless channels, AirComp | enables simultaneous aggregation of signals from multiple
  L061: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 13 --
  L060: antenna and multi-antenna environments. This highlights its | potential for deployment in practical, large-scale wireless | scenarios.
  L109: AirComp-based distributed inference framework using real- | world wireless hardware setups, further assessing practical per- | formance and robustness. In addition, exploring cluster-based
  L110: world wireless hardware setups, further assessing practical per- | formance and robustness. In addition, exploring cluster-based | hierarchical AirComp designs and distributed transceiver opti-
  L135: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 14 --
  L157: [3] Y. Chang, X. Wang, J. Wang, Y. Wu, L. Yang, K. Zhu, H. Chen, X. Yi, | C. Wang, Y. Wang, et al., 鈥淎 survey on evaluation of large language | models,鈥?ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol., vol. 15, no. 3, pp. 1鈥?5,
  L158: C. Wang, Y. Wang, et al., 鈥淎 survey on evaluation of large language | models,鈥?ACM Trans. Intell. Syst. Technol., vol. 15, no. 3, pp. 1鈥?5, | 2024.
  L166: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 15 --
  L001: 15 | [5] H. Fan, X. Liu, J. Y. H. Fuh, W. F. Lu, and B. Li, 鈥淓mbodied intelligence | in manufacturing: leveraging large language models for autonomous
  L003: in manufacturing: leveraging large language models for autonomous | industrial robotics,鈥?J. Intell. Manuf., pp. 1鈥?7, 2024. | [6] Y. Yang, T. Zhou, K. Li, D. Tao, L. Li, L. Shen, X. He, J. Jiang, and
  L015: [9] J. Shao, J. Tong, Q. Wu, W. Guo, Z. Li, Z. Lin, and J. Zhang, | 鈥淲irelessLLM: Empowering large language models towards wireless | intelligence,鈥?J. Commun. Inf. Netw., vol. 9, pp. 99鈥?12, 2024.
  L016: 鈥淲irelessLLM: Empowering large language models towards wireless | intelligence,鈥?J. Commun. Inf. Netw., vol. 9, pp. 99鈥?12, 2024. | [10] J. Tong, J. Shao, Q. Wu, W. Guo, Z. Li, Z. Lin, and J. Zhang,
  L018: [10] J. Tong, J. Shao, Q. Wu, W. Guo, Z. Li, Z. Lin, and J. Zhang, | 鈥淲irelessAgent: Large language model agents for intelligent wireless | networks,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2409.07964, 2024.
  L042: [15] K. B. Letaief, W. Chen, Y. Shi, J. Zhang, and Y.-J. A. Zhang, 鈥淭he | roadmap to 6G: AI empowered wireless networks,鈥?IEEE Commun. | Mag., vol. 57, no. 8, pp. 84鈥?0, 2019.
  L044: Mag., vol. 57, no. 8, pp. 84鈥?0, 2019. | [16] K. B. Letaief, Y. Shi, J. Lu, and J. Lu, 鈥淓dge artificial intelligence for | 6G: Vision, enabling technologies, and applications,鈥?IEEE J. Sel. Areas
  L052: S. Guo, 鈥淗igh efficiency inference accelerating algorithm for noma- | based edge intelligence,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 23, no. 11, | pp. 17539鈥?7556, 2024.
  L059: [20] Y. Chen, R. Li, X. Yu, Z. Zhao, and H. Zhang, 鈥淎daptive layer | splitting for wireless LLM inference in edge computing: A model-based | reinforcement learning approach,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2406.02616,
  L089: IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory, vol. 53, no. 10, pp. 3498鈥?516, 2007. | [30] S. Cui, J.-J. Xiao, A. J. Goldsmith, Z.-Q. Luo, and H. V. Poor, 鈥淓nergy- | efficient joint estimation in sensor networks: Analog vs. digital,鈥?in IEEE
  L094: [31] F. Wang and V. K. Lau, 鈥淢ulti-level over-the-air aggregation of mobile | edge computing over d2d wireless networks,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless | Commun., vol. 21, no. 10, pp. 8337鈥?353, 2022.
  L099: 5755, 2021. | [33] X. Cao, G. Zhu, J. Xu, and K. Huang, 鈥淥ptimized power control | for over-the-air computation in fading channels,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless
  L100: [33] X. Cao, G. Zhu, J. Xu, and K. Huang, 鈥淥ptimized power control | for over-the-air computation in fading channels,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless | Commun., vol. 19, no. 11, pp. 7498鈥?513, 2020.
  L103: [34] K. Yang, T. Jiang, Y. Shi, and Z. Ding, 鈥淔ederated learning via over- | the-air computation,鈥?IEEE transactions on wireless communications, | vol. 19, no. 3, pp. 2022鈥?035, 2020.
  L112: [37] Z. Liu, Q. Lan, A. E. Kalor, P. Popovski, and K. Huang, 鈥淥ver-the- | air multi-view pooling for distributed sensing,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless | Commun., vol. 23, no. 7, pp. 7652鈥?667, 2023.
  L121: [40] X. Fan, Y. Wang, Y. Huo, and Z. Tian, 鈥淛oint optimization of com- | munications and federated learning over the air,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless | Commun., vol. 21, no. 6, pp. 4434鈥?449, 2021.
  L124: [41] Y. Liang, Q. Chen, G. Zhu, H. Jiang, Y. C. Eldar, and S. Cui, | 鈥淐ommunication-and-energy efficient over-the-air federated learning,鈥?| IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 767鈥?82, 2025.
  L125: 鈥淐ommunication-and-energy efficient over-the-air federated learning,鈥?| IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 767鈥?82, 2025. | [42] H. Sun, H. Tian, W. Ni, J. Zheng, D. Niyato, and P. Zhang, 鈥淔ed-
  L127: [42] H. Sun, H. Tian, W. Ni, J. Zheng, D. Niyato, and P. Zhang, 鈥淔ed- | erated low-rank adaptation for large models fine-tuning over wireless | networks,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 659鈥?75,
  L128: erated low-rank adaptation for large models fine-tuning over wireless | networks,鈥?IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 24, no. 1, pp. 659鈥?75, | 2025.
  L130: 2025. | [43] Z. Zhuang, D. Wen, Y. Shi, G. Zhu, S. Wu, and D. Niyato, 鈥淚ntegrated | sensing-communication-computation for over-the-air edge AI inference,鈥?
  L132: sensing-communication-computation for over-the-air edge AI inference,鈥?| IEEE Trans. Wireless Commun., vol. 23, no. 4, pp. 3205鈥?220, 2023. | [44] P. Yang, D. Wen, Q. Zeng, Y. Zhou, T. Wang, H. Cai, and Y. Shi, 鈥淥ver-
  L134: [44] P. Yang, D. Wen, Q. Zeng, Y. Zhou, T. Wang, H. Cai, and Y. Shi, 鈥淥ver- | the-air computation empowered vertically split inference,鈥?IEEE Trans. | Wireless Commun., vol. 23, no. 12, pp. 19634鈥?9648, 2024.
  L135: the-air computation empowered vertically split inference,鈥?IEEE Trans. | Wireless Commun., vol. 23, no. 12, pp. 19634鈥?9648, 2024. | [45] A. Vaswani, N. Shazeer, N. Parmar, J. Uszkoreit, L. Jones, A. N. Gomez,
  L140: [46] M. Goldenbaum, H. Boche, and S. Sta麓nczak, 鈥淗arnessing interference | for analog function computation in wireless sensor networks,鈥?IEEE | Trans. Signal Process., vol. 61, no. 20, pp. 4893鈥?906, 2013.
-- page 16 --
  L009: perplexity,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.14132, 2023. | [59] D. Tse and P. Viswanath, Fundamentals of wireless communication. | Cambridge university press, 2005.
  L011: Cambridge university press, 2005. | [60] A. Goldsmith, Wireless communications. Cambridge university press, | 2005.
  L020: University of Science and Technology. His research | interests include edge intelligence and federated | learning.
  L036: Southeast University. | His areas of interests currently include machine learning for wireless | communications, edge AI and wireless sensing. He was the recipient of the
  L037: His areas of interests currently include machine learning for wireless | communications, edge AI and wireless sensing. He was the recipient of the | first prize of the Natural Science Award of the Chinese Institute of Electronics
  L041: and Jiangsu Province in 2022, and Top 2% Scientists Worldwide 2023 | and 2024 by Stanford University. He is the Editor of IEEE WIRELESS | COMMUNICATIONS LETTERS.
  L045: Assistant Professor jointly appointed by the Division | of Integrative Systems and Design and the Depart- | ment of Electronic and Computer Engineering at the
  L050: less Communications and Machine Learning with | current focus on Distributed Intelligence, Semantic | Communications, Machine Learning for Commu-
  L052: Communications, Machine Learning for Commu- | nications, Integrated Sensing and Communication, | and Information Theory. Dr. Song is an editorial
  L074: Kong University of Science and Technology. His | research interests include wireless communications | and networking, mobile edge computing and edge
  L076: and networking, mobile edge computing and edge | AI, and integrated AI and communications. He is an | IEEE Fellow and an IEEE ComSoc Distinguished
  L084: Society Joint Paper Award, and the 2016 Marconi Prize Paper Award in | Wireless Communications. Two papers he co-authored received the Young | Author Best Paper Award of the IEEE Signal Processing Society in 2016
  L088: Best Young Researcher Award. He is an Area Editor of IEEE Transactions | on Wireless Communications and IEEE Transactions on Machine Learning | in Communications and Networking. He served as a MAC track co-chair for
  L090: in Communications and Networking. He served as a MAC track co-chair for | IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC) 2011, | a co-chair for the Wireless Communications Symposium of IEEE International
  L091: IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC) 2011, | a co-chair for the Wireless Communications Symposium of IEEE International | Conference on Communications (ICC) 2021, and a TPC co-chair for The IEEE
  L093: Conference on Communications (ICC) 2021, and a TPC co-chair for The IEEE | Hong Kong 6G Wireless Summit 2023, 2024. | Khaled B. Letaief (S鈥?5-M鈥?6-SM鈥?7-F鈥?3) is a
  L095: Khaled B. Letaief (S鈥?5-M鈥?6-SM鈥?7-F鈥?3) is a | globally recognized leader in wireless communica- | tions and networks, with a research focus that spans
  L097: tions and networks, with a research focus that spans | artificial intelligence, integrated sensing and commu- | nication, mobile cloud and edge computing, tactile
  L117: Society and Information Theory Society, the 2016 IEEE Marconi Prize Award | in Wireless Communications, and over 20 IEEE Best Paper Awards. | Since 1993, Dr. Letaief has been a faculty member at The Hong Kong
  L122: Head of the Electronic and Computer Engineering Department, Director of | the Wireless IC Design Center, and Director of the Hong Kong Telecom | Institute of Information Technology. He served as Chair Professor and Dean
  L132: Director and member of the IEEE Board of Directors, founding Editor-in- | Chief of the esteemed IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, and | President of the IEEE Communications Society from 2018 to 2019, the leading
  L142: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/JSTSP.2025.3581478 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.

========== Zhang 绛?- 2025 - Beyond the Cloud Edge Inference for Generative Large Language Models in Wireless Networks - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L000: IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | 643
  L003: Beyond the Cloud: Edge Inference for Generative | Large Language Models in Wireless Networks | Xinyuan Zhang , Graduate Student Member, IEEE, Jiangtian Nie ,
  L008: and Xuemin Shen , Fellow, IEEE | Abstract鈥?Generative Artificial Intelligenge (GAI) is revolu- | tionizing the world with its unprecedented content creation
  L014: privacy, usage limitations, and latency. In this paper, we pro- | pose to utilize ubiquitous distributed wireless edge computing | resources for real-time LLM inference. Specifically, we introduce
  L032: Communications Research and Development Program; in part by the Defence | Science Organization (DSO) National Laboratories under the Artificial Intel- | ligence (AI) Singapore Program; in part by Singapore Ministry of Education
  L076: time complexity reduction compared to brute-force searching. | Index Terms鈥?Generative AI, edge inference, wireless net- | works, multiuser edge computing.
  L081: UST as electricity transformed the world a century ago, | Artificial Intelligence (AI) is now revolutionizing our daily | life [1]. A significant milestone in this evolution is Generative
  L097: and innovative solutions. | Wireless edge networks offer a promising complement | to cloud-based LLM inference. By harnessing ubiquitous
  L099: to cloud-based LLM inference. By harnessing ubiquitous | edge computing power, LLM service capacity is amplified. | Besides, deploying LLMs on nearby edge nodes circumvents
  L107: computations, none of them has explicitly tackled the chal- | lenges related to LLM inference in wireless edge networks. | Exploring LLM inference in wireless edge networks is
  L108: lenges related to LLM inference in wireless edge networks. | Exploring LLM inference in wireless edge networks is | crucial due to LLM鈥檚 distinct attributes compared with other
-- page 2 --
  L001: 644 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Fig. 1.
  L020: challenging. Although [15] delved into joint LLM caching and | inference in wireless edge networks, it overlooked LLMs鈥?sig- | nificant size, extensive memory footprint, and computational
  L032: transformer-based LLM inference framework for mobile | users in wireless edge networks. As shown in Fig. 1, LLM | service providers (LSPs) cooperate with cloud computing
  L035: providers (CCPs) for LLM deployment and inference. CCPs | employ edge computing power, such as UAVs over hotspot | zones or vehicles in dense areas, to augment their services and
  L037: zones or vehicles in dense areas, to augment their services and | ensure instant delivery via wireless networks. Mobile users | can conveniently access LLM services in a pay-as-you-go
  L041: framework. First, is it feasible to run resource-intensive | LLM inference on resource-limited wireless edge nodes? | Second, how can we assess the LLM service quality and
  L046: to conserve memory footprint during LLM edge inference | by storing model weights and activations with reduced | bit precision [6], [16]. To address the second challenge,
  L056: timeliness, blog creation is less time-sensitive. Thus, latency | is also considered for service quality evaluation. Furthermore, | our framework utilize batching to compute multiple user
  L059: requests parallelly [18], [19], boosting the inference capability | of wireless edge networks. | Based on the above framework, we propose an LLM
  L078: 鈥?We introduce the LLM edge inference framework tailored | for wireless networks, incorporating model quantization | and batching techniques to enhance inference through-
-- page 3 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 645
  L063: in the game Mount&Blade 2, typing-based dialogues with | GPT-empowered NPCs introduce 3 to 5 seconds of latency, | notably affecting player experience [27].
  L076: services. Besides, the authors in [15] explored joint LLM | caching and inference in wireless edge networks, and intro- | duced a novel metric 鈥渁ge of context鈥?to evaluate the freshness
  L081: looked the challenges of LLM inference in resource-limited | wireless edge networks, which arises from LLMs鈥?super large | model size, autoregressive generation process, and resource-
  L097: LLM inference. In [14], the authors enhanced the throughput | of latency-insensitive LLM tasks on a single GPU, incorporat- | ing dynamic batch size adjustments, optimized tensor storage
  L108: our work lies in enhancing the access availability of GAI | services in the wireless network domain. [19] bears a close | resemblance to our research, but it was based on traditional
  L116: lower bits [16]. This technique is crucial for making LLMs | manageable and efficient on wireless edge nodes, given their | large size and computational demands. Generally, there are
-- page 4 --
  L001: 646 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Fig. 2.
  L013: features. This approach efficiently ran OPT-175B on a con- | sumer GPU server without performance losses. In our study, | we adopt some outstanding LLM quantization schemes in
  L015: we adopt some outstanding LLM quantization schemes in | wireless edge networks and design two metrics to represent | the effect of quantization on memory savings and computa-
  L021: III. MODELS AND METRICS | Consider a wireless edge network that comprises multiple | users, multiple edge nodes, multiple access points, and a
-- page 5 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 647
  L006: ij, remaining consistent within one epoch. The uplink and | downlink transmission power are given by pU | ij and pD
  L011: nodes can estimate the channel gain and uplink transmission | power. This data is then forwarded to the server controller | for bandwidth allocation. However, if the information is not
  L030: , | where N0 is the white Gaussian channel noise power. The | downlink communication rate rD
-- page 6 --
  L001: 648 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Batching is a key to enhance the throughput, measured
  L021: extreme latency for users, which instead leads to throughput | reduction. This necessitates intelligent batching scheduling to | balance the tradeoff. Hence, in the following, we analyze the
-- page 7 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 649
  L037: In this section, we first introduce the LLM edge inference | optimization problem in wireless networks, aimed at maxi- | mizing throughput while adhering to constraints of bandwidth,
  L054: its greedy search. We also introduce a tree-pruning method to | bypass exploring redundant branches. Lastly, we return to the | original problem. As it can be seen as a Generalized Assign-
  L067: variable, the LLM edge inference optimization problem for | the whole wireless network is formulated as follows: | P1: max
-- page 8 --
  L001: 650 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Fig. 5.
-- page 9 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 651
  L064: constraints into Problem P3. This means that in addition to z, | 藴蟿i and ni in Algorithm 1, we now need to integrate two addi- | tional metrics, 蟻U
  L084: i,min in (2), reveals that the downlink | transmit power of the edge node, denoted as pD, remains | consistent for all users. Furthermore, the edge node can obtain
-- page 10 --
  L001: 652 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | of FNk. With Fd established, we aim to identify a potential
  L112: 1) Tree-search: To answer the first question, two funda- | mental search strategies follow. Firstly, when exploring all | child nodes of any node, preference is given to the one with
-- page 11 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 653
  L087: a given z and 蟿min, the OT algorithm structures the solution | space as a tree, factoring in constraints like uplink bandwidth, | downlink bandwidth, memory, and latency. It then performs
  L154: which is polynomial in terms of I and J, with J representing | the number of edge nodes within a wireless network. | Algorithm 3 Optimal Tree-Search With Generalized Assign-
-- page 12 --
  L001: 654 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | V. SIMULATIONS
  L021: An edge server, an UAV, and a vehicle are placed in a | wireless network. In the simulation, the edge server is assumed | to be equipped with 20 NVIDIA JETSON TX2 GPUs, each
  L022: wireless network. In the simulation, the edge server is assumed | to be equipped with 20 NVIDIA JETSON TX2 GPUs, each | with 1.33TFLOPs and 32GB memory. The edge server is
  L025: placed together with a base station. The uplink and downlink | bandwidth are 20MHz, the transmit power from users to the | base station is 20dBm, and the transmit power from the base
  L026: bandwidth are 20MHz, the transmit power from users to the | base station is 20dBm, and the transmit power from the base | station to users is 43dBm [38]. N0 = 鈭?74dBm/Hz. The
  L029: channel gain follows Rayleigh fading with average path loss | as 10鈭? [19]. The UAV is assumed to carry a TX2 GPU and | fly at the height of 100m, which is within the free-space path
  L032: loss. The uplink and downlink bandwidth are both 1MHz. The | transmit power between the UAV and a user is 10dBm [39], | [40]. The vehicle is assumed to be equipped with three TX2
  L036: stations. The uplink and downlink bandwidth are both 2MHz. | The transmit power from the base station to the vehicle is | 30dBm, and the transmit power from the vehicle to the base
  L037: The transmit power from the base station to the vehicle is | 30dBm, and the transmit power from the vehicle to the base | station in 23dBm. The pathloss and slow fading model follows
  L046: tion, the implemented LLM, and the requisite input and | output lengths to ensure there is no GPU overflow. During | each epoch, the edge node aggregates prompts, either of
  L051: uplink communication slots and wait in a first-in-first-out | queue. When any GPU is idle, the edge node accepts | the request at the queue head, executes inference on that
  L053: the request at the queue head, executes inference on that | single GPU without batching. During execution, if the | accumulated uploading, waiting, and computing latency
-- page 13 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 655
  L010: scheme, in contrast, fails to leverage parallel computing. The | single GPU鈥檚 processing speed is quite limited, resulting | in most requests being dropped. Furthermore, BLOOM-7.1B
  L047: attributed to its streamlined tensor dimensions and fewer | matrix operations. In no-batching, a single GPU starts to | satisfy the deadline for large-scale BLOOM-7.1B inferences
-- page 14 --
  L001: 656 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Fig. 13.
  L042: In this paper, we have investigated the ubiquitous access | to generative LLM services by leveraging wireless edge net- | works. We have studied the LLM edge inference optimization
  L058: tion of quantization schemes tailored for specific LLMs | in resource-limited wireless edge networks. In future work, | we will delve deeper into more scalable GAI offloading
  L066: [1] C.-X. Wang, M. D. Renzo, S. Stanczak, S. Wang, and E. G. Larsson, | 鈥淎rtificial intelligence enabled wireless networking for 5G and beyond: | Recent advances and future challenges,鈥?IEEE Wireless Commun.,
  L067: 鈥淎rtificial intelligence enabled wireless networking for 5G and beyond: | Recent advances and future challenges,鈥?IEEE Wireless Commun., | vol. 27, no. 1, pp. 16鈥?3, Feb. 2020.
  L077: [5] X. Zhang, J. Liu, Z. Xiong, Y. Huang, G. Xie, and R. Zhang, 鈥淓dge | intelligence optimization for large language model inference with batch- | ing and quantization,鈥?2024, arXiv:2405.07140.
  L081: arXiv:2303.18223. | [7] M. Xu et al., 鈥淯nleashing the power of edge-cloud generative AI in | mobile networks: A survey of AIGC services,鈥?2023, arXiv:2303.16129.
  L083: mobile networks: A survey of AIGC services,鈥?2023, arXiv:2303.16129. | [8] H. Du et al., 鈥淓nabling AI-generated content (AIGC) services in wireless | edge networks,鈥?2023, arXiv:2301.03220.
  L085: edge networks,鈥?2023, arXiv:2301.03220. | [9] H. Du et al., 鈥淓xploring collaborative distributed diffusion-based AI- | generated content (AIGC) in wireless networks,鈥?IEEE Netw., vol. 38,
  L086: [9] H. Du et al., 鈥淓xploring collaborative distributed diffusion-based AI- | generated content (AIGC) in wireless networks,鈥?IEEE Netw., vol. 38, | no. 3, pp. 1鈥?, May 2024.
  L099: [14] Y. Sheng et al., 鈥淗igh-throughput generative inference of large language | models with a single GPU,鈥?2023, arXiv:2303.06865. | [15] M. Xu et al., 鈥淛oint foundation model caching and inference of gener-
  L101: [15] M. Xu et al., 鈥淛oint foundation model caching and inference of gener- | ative AI services for edge intelligence,鈥?2023, arXiv:2305.12130. | [16] M. Nagel, M. Fournarakis, R. A. Amjad, Y. Bondarenko, M. van Baalen,
-- page 15 --
  L000: ZHANG et al.: BEYOND THE CLOUD: EDGE INFERENCE FOR GENERATIVE LLMs IN WIRELESS NETWORKS | 657
  L015: Association, 2022, pp. 521鈥?38. | [21] L. Yunjiu, W. Wei, and Y. Zheng, 鈥淎rtificial intelligence-generated and | human expert-designed vocabulary tests: A comparative study,鈥?Sage
  L059: computing for continuous applications under uncertainty,鈥?IEEE Trans. | Wireless Commun., vol. 19, no. 9, pp. 6196鈥?209, Sep. 2020. | [32] R. Cohen, L. Katzir, and D. Raz, 鈥淎n efficient approximation for the
  L064: [33] T. Zhu, J. Li, Z. Cai, Y. Li, and H. Gao, 鈥淐omputation scheduling for | wireless powered mobile edge computing networks,鈥?in Proc. INFO- | COM. Toronto, ON, Canada: IEEE, 2020, pp. 596鈥?05.
  L075: Systems). Agartala, Tripura, India: Springer, 2021, pp. 193鈥?00. | [37] F. Stollenwerk, 鈥淭raining and evaluation of a multilingual tokenizer for | GPT-SW3,鈥?2023, arXiv:2304.14780.
  L091: vol. 69, no. 10, pp. 11975鈥?1991, Oct. 2020. | [42] NVIDIA. NVIDIA AI Inference Platform Technical Overview. Accessed: | Oct. 13, 2023. [Online]. Available: https://www.nvidia.com/content/dam/
  L092: [42] NVIDIA. NVIDIA AI Inference Platform Technical Overview. Accessed: | Oct. 13, 2023. [Online]. Available: https://www.nvidia.com/content/dam/ | en-zz/Solutions/Data-Center/tesla-product-literature/t4-inference-print-
  L111: Singapore, in 2022. Her current research interests | include satellite-terrestrial integrated networks, edge | intelligence, and generative AI.
  L112: include satellite-terrestrial integrated networks, edge | intelligence, and generative AI. | Jiangtian
  L141: interests include time-sensitive networks, determin- | istic networks, and network intelligence. | Gaochang Xie (Graduate Student Member, IEEE)
  L152: Singapore, since May 2023. His current research | interests include edge intelligence and the Internet of | Vehicles.
-- page 16 --
  L001: 658 | IEEE TRANSACTIONS ON WIRELESS COMMUNICATIONS, VOL. 24, NO. 1, JANUARY 2025 | Zehui Xiong (Senior Member, IEEE) received the
  L011: versity of Waterloo. His research interests include | wireless communications, the Internet of Things, | blockchain, edge intelligence, and metaverse. Recog-
  L012: wireless communications, the Internet of Things, | blockchain, edge intelligence, and metaverse. Recog- | nized as a Highly Cited Researcher, he has published more than 300 research
  L046: networking (SDN), information-centric networking (ICN), and network | testbed. | Dusit Niyato (Fellow, IEEE) received the B.Eng.
  L053: research interests inlcude mobile generative AI, | edge intelligence, decentralized machine learning, | and incentive mechanism design. He is currently
  L064: University of Waterloo, Canada. His research inter- | ests include network resource management, wireless | network security, the Internet of Things, 5G and
  L080: in 2015, the Education Award from the IEEE Communications Society | (ComSoc), in 2017, and Technical Recognition Award from the Wireless | Communications Technical Committee in 2019 and the AHSN Technical
  L088: and 07, IEEE Infocom鈥?4, and IEEE VTC鈥?0 Fall, and the Chair for the | IEEE ComSoc Technical Committee on Wireless Communications. He was | the President of the IEEE ComSoc, the Vice President of Technical &

========== Zhu 绛?- 2025 - Birds in Cages Edge Inference Allocation for Distributed LLM Deployment - .pdf ==========
-- page 5 --
  L087: accordingly. Otherwise, the task will be abandoned. | V. PERFORMANCE EVALUATION | A. Settings
  L106: 鈭圼40, 200]. | Considering the parameters of edge intelligence devices like | NVIDIA Jetson Orin [10], the number of edge servers is
  L107: Considering the parameters of edge intelligence devices like | NVIDIA Jetson Orin [10], the number of edge servers is | J = 60, computation resources are Cj 鈭圼20, 50] TFLOPs
-- page 6 --
  L113: [1] Liekang Zeng, Shengyuan Ye, Xu Chen, and Yang Yang. Implemen- | tation of big ai models for wireless networks with collaborative edge | computing. IEEE Wireless Communications, 31(3):50鈥?8, 2024.
  L114: tation of big ai models for wireless networks with collaborative edge | computing. IEEE Wireless Communications, 31(3):50鈥?8, 2024. | [2] Bingyang Wu, Yinmin Zhong, Zili Zhang, Shengyu Liu, Fangyue
  L122: Xiong, Jiang Liu, Dusit Niyato, and Xuemin Sherman Shen. Beyond the | cloud: Edge inference for generative large language models in wireless | networks. IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 2024. Early
  L123: cloud: Edge inference for generative large language models in wireless | networks. IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 2024. Early | Access, doi: 10.1109/TWC.2024.3497923.
  L152: inference acceleration based on multi-dimensional optimization for edge | intelligence. | IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing, 22(9):5389鈥?
  L156: [11] Yulong He, Xiaofan He, Richeng Jin, and Huaiyu Dai. Location privacy- | aware and energy-ef铿乧ient of铿俹ading for distributed edge computing. | IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 22(11):7975鈥?988,
  L157: aware and energy-ef铿乧ient of铿俹ading for distributed edge computing. | IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, 22(11):7975鈥?988, | 2023.

========== Xu 绛?- 2025 - Joint Inference Offloading and Model Caching for Small and Large Language Model Collaboration - .pdf ==========
-- page 1 --
  L008: content creation and inference capabilities, can provide immer- | sive intelligent services to users in mobile edge networks. How- | ever, the increasing demand for real-time artificial intelligence
  L009: sive intelligent services to users in mobile edge networks. How- | ever, the increasing demand for real-time artificial intelligence | (AI) applications aggravates the limitations of cloud-based LLMs
  L041: tional capabilities in capturing complex patterns in language | and context, for supporting immersive intelligent services | like metaverse and smart cities [3]. As the next generation
  L043: like metaverse and smart cities [3]. As the next generation | wireless system (6G) aims to go far beyond the scope of | traditional communication services, LLMs are emerging as
  L046: one of the most promising enablers for advancing endogenous | intelligence for 6G [4]. | Due to high computational complexity of LLM inference, it
  L055: Xinyi Xu, Gang Feng, Yijing Liu, Shuang Qin, Jian Wang, Yunxiang Wang | are with the National Key Laboratory of Wireless Communications, University | of Electronic Science and Technology of China, Chengdu 611731, China
  L063: chitecture has become a promising solution, driven by the | advancements in GPU performance and model compression | techniques [7], [8]. However, LLM inference involves complex
  L075: user privacy and meeting strict latency constraints. However, | the intelligence capabilities of SLMs deployed on terminal | devices may be limited by model size and computation
  L080: perspectives. From the model perspective, recent studies have | demonstrated that integrating domain-specialized SLMs as | plug-ins for LLMs can enhance the performance of LLMs
  L094: arises from resource-constrained edge environments where | GPU memory and bandwidth are limited, making it infeasible | to cache all user-side SLMs as plug-ins for the LLM at the
  L106: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 2 --
  L009: collaboration schemes have primarily focused on either model- | level enhancements, such as plug-in integration, or task-level | offloading strategies [11], [13]. For instance, an inference
  L011: offloading strategies [11], [13]. For instance, an inference | framework that integrates domain-specialized SLMs as plug- | ins for LLMs is proposed in [11]. A task offloading scheme
  L091: The recent advent of LLMs has been a milestone in AI | technology to enable general-purpose intelligence. Due to the | associated computing and memory costs, existing LLMs are
  L094: mostly confined to cloud data centers for service provisioning. | The authors of [14] proposed an LLM-empowered framework | to perform fully automatic network intrusion detection by
  L097: deploying a pre-trained LLM on cloud for network security | monitoring. The authors of [15] introduced a cloud-based | GPU allocation framework that derives the minimal-cost GPU
  L098: monitoring. The authors of [15] introduced a cloud-based | GPU allocation framework that derives the minimal-cost GPU | allocation for a given LLM service. An LLM serving system
  L107: for the users behind radio access networks. Therefore, some | investigators considered the integration of LLMs and edge | computing. The authors of [17] proposed a joint caching and
  L109: computing. The authors of [17] proposed a joint caching and | inference framework to provide intelligence services in space- | air-ground integrated networks by deploying LLM on edge
  L110: inference framework to provide intelligence services in space- | air-ground integrated networks by deploying LLM on edge | servers and cloud data center. The authors of [13] proposed
  L117: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 3 --
  L006: training on edge servers, followed by federated fine-tuning | on edge devices. In addition, a lightweight LLM-powered | ranking framework, RankExpert, is proposed in [19] to inte-
  L012: user satisfaction. Although the aforementioned investigations | considered the integration of LLM and edge computing, the | proposals of [3], [17]鈥揫19] and [13] still cannot meet the needs
  L023: computing nodes. The authors of [20] introduced a collab- | orative inference framework with integrated pruning, where | a pre-trained LLM is jointly pruned and partitioned between
  L030: (UE) and the edge server to improve inference efficiency | under varying wireless network conditions. A split computing | framework for generative AI, called 螞-split, was proposed
  L035: computational efficiency. In addition, a task-oriented sens- | ing鈥揷omputation鈥揷ommunication integration framework was | introduced in [23],where multiple edge devices perform lo-
  L043: native LLM鈥揝LM collaborative inference paradigm, where | heterogeneous SLMs and powerful LLMs are deployed on | deployed across network nodes, such as user devices and edge
  L067: Ni | The set of neighboring users of UE i | |mi|
  L134: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 4 --
  L017: edge server typically has sufficient computation resources and | transmit power, we ignore the downlink transmission time of | the inference results [25].
  L049: three inference task processing choices: (a) local processing on the device, | (b) offloading to a neighboring user through D2D link, (c) offloading to edge | sever via a cellular link.
  L111: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 5 --
  L018: SLM for processing text has millions of parameters [26], and | definitely occupies certain Graphics Processing Unit (GPU) | memory space. Obviously, we cannot cache all the SLMs at
  L020: memory space. Obviously, we cannot cache all the SLMs at | the edge server鈥檚 GPU at the same time. Let G denote the | amount of GPU memory available on the edge server for
  L021: the edge server鈥檚 GPU at the same time. Let G denote the | amount of GPU memory available on the edge server for | caching SLMs, and let 蟻 denote the memory consumption
  L031: (1) | It is worth noting that constraining GPU memory usage also | implicitly limits the energy consumption associated with SLM
  L032: It is worth noting that constraining GPU memory usage also | implicitly limits the energy consumption associated with SLM | caching. Since memory access and model inference on GPUs
  L034: caching. Since memory access and model inference on GPUs | are major contributors to edge server energy consumption | [27], especially under sustained workloads, bounding the total
  L037: memory footprint naturally curtails the computational and | energy load incurred by maintaining and activating multiple | SLMs.
  L043: tasks to the edge server through cellular links or to their | neighboring users through D2D links. The bandwidth of the | system is denoted by B. To avoid interference between cellular
  L062: (2) | where pi,t denotes the transmit power from user i during time | slot t, Gi,t denotes the channel gain from user i to BS during
  L064: slot t, Gi,t denotes the channel gain from user i to BS during | time slot t. 蟽2 represents the power spectral density of the | white noise. Therefore, the transmission rate between BS and
  L075: UE i. Let us present a simple communication protocol to deter- | mine the set of neighboring UEs for each UE [33]. Essentially, | we let UE j be able to communicate with UE i at coordinate
  L129: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 6 --
  L019: Offload to | neighboring | user j
  L057: locally, offloaded to the edge server, or offloaded to the | neighboring users. When an inference task request occurs, the | task offloading protocol is as follows:
  L062: cached on the edge server to infer the task collaboratively. | (c) Offloading to the neighboring user: Use the SLM de- | ployed on the neighboring user to infer the task.
  L063: (c) Offloading to the neighboring user: Use the SLM de- | ployed on the neighboring user to infer the task. | The computation capacity of the edge server is denoted as
  L075: Similarly, if the task Tki,t requested by user i in time slot t is | offloaded to neighboring user j through D2D communication | for calculation and inference, the resultant computation latency
  L157: server, the decisions of each user to offload inference tasks | to neighboring users, and the decisions of each user to offload | inference tasks to edge server, respectively. qi,t (尾, 纬, 伪) =
  L168: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 7 --
  L012: nication round r. Constraint (6-1) means that the user can | offload its inference task to one neighboring user in a time | slot. Constraint (6-2) states that a user can only choose one
  L016: to transmit the inference task in a time slot. The latency re- | quirements of inference tasks and the GPU memory occupied | by SLMs cached on the edge server are constrained in (6-
  L132: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 8 --
  L055: Reward : In order to maximize the long-term inference | accuracy while satisfying the GPU memory constraints of the | edge server, we define the reward function as
  L085: (9) | If the GPU memory usage of cached SLMs exceeds the | available capacity, a penalty 尉 will be imposed. Otherwise,
  L193: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 9 --
  L043: algorithm, which is commonly used in decoding processes | like LDPC code decoding in wireless communications, excels | in iteratively propagating probabilistic information between
  L063: is the decision variable indicating whether user i chooses to | offload the task to neighboring user j at time slot t. Therefore, | the inference accuracy of the task requested by user i in time
  L071: denotes the inference accuracy of the task requested by user | i when offloaded to the edge server, neighboring users, or | processed locally in time slot t. Thus, sub-problem (7) can be
  L285: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 10 --
  L020: (23) | where 尉 (i, j) represents the index of neighboring user i in the | set L (i). The mapping rule from 畏
  L272: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 11 --
  L061: We consider an MEC system with one edge server co- | located with BS and 3 UEs in a wireless communication sce- | nario within a range of 100m脳100m. The users are randomly
  L064: distributed in the area. And the network topology is according | to Fig. 5a. The noise power spectral density is assumed to be | 鈭?74dBm/Hz [42]. The cellular channel model is assumed
  L079: BERT-large model in FP16 requires approximately 1.2GB of | GPU memory, which can be readily supported by modern | edge GPUs. Considering the different computation capabilities
  L086: Uplink / D2D link transmit | power | 23 dBm
  L088: 23 dBm | Noise power spectral density | -174 dBm/Hz
  L153: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 12 --
  L004: Fig. 7. The accumulated reward of LSCI, SIRB, and LSRG. | power is set to 23 dBm, system bandwidth is set to 15 MHz. | As shown in Fig. 8, LSCI always outperforms than the other
  L014: transmission rate and inference accuracy for four algorithms | by changing the transmit power and bandwidth. First, we | examine the AIA as a function of the transmit power. Fig. 9
  L015: by changing the transmit power and bandwidth. First, we | examine the AIA as a function of the transmit power. Fig. 9 | shows the AIA versus the transmit power of users. We can see
  L016: examine the AIA as a function of the transmit power. Fig. 9 | shows the AIA versus the transmit power of users. We can see | that the AIA achieved by LSCI is always higher than that of
  L019: SIRB, SLWP, and LSRG. The AIA increases with the transmit | power of users. Especially, when transmit power is 26 dBm, | the AIA achieved by LSCI can reach 0.841, which is 2.44%
  L024: AIA as a function of the system bandwidth, when the transmit | power is fixed to 23 dBm. As shown in Fig. 12, the AIA | achieved by four algorithms monotonically increases with the
  L029: Fig. 8. The inference accuracy of different types of tasks versus algorithms. | Fig. 9. The impact of transmit power on AIA. | the system bandwidth is greater than 7.5 MHz, demonstrating
  L056: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 13 --
  L027: communication modes. The system bandwidth is set to 15 | MHz, and transmit power is set to 23 dBm. As shown in Fig. | Fig. 12. The impact of system bandwidth on AIA.
  L054: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 14 --
  L137: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 15 --
  L004: hensive study on cost-efficiency trade-off between communi- | cation resource and computing power for provisioning typical | AI inference services, under real network architectures with
  L017: [3] M. Xu, D. Niyato, H. Zhang, J. Kang, Z. Xiong, S. Mao, and Z. Han, | 鈥淪parks of GPTs in edge intelligence for metaverse: Caching and | inference for mobile AIGC services,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.08782,
  L022: A. Jamalipour, D. I. Kim, X. Shen, V. C. M. Leung, and H. V. Poor, | 鈥淯nleashing the power of edge-cloud generative ai in mobile networks: | A survey of aigc services,鈥?IEEE Communications Surveys & Tutorials,
  L042: black-box large language models with small domain-specific models,鈥?in | Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, vol. 39, | no. 23, 2025, pp. 24 422鈥?4 430.
  L049: [12] B. Hu, Q. Sheng, J. Cao, Y. Shi, Y. Li, D. Wang, and P. Qi, 鈥淏ad | actor, good advisor: Exploring the role of large language models in fake | news detection,鈥?in Proceedings of the AAAI conference on artificial
  L051: news detection,鈥?in Proceedings of the AAAI conference on artificial | intelligence, vol. 38, no. 20, 2024, pp. 22 105鈥?2 113. | [13] Y. He, J. Fang, F. R. Yu, and V. C. Leung, 鈥淟arge language models
  L057: [14] H. Zhang, A. B. Sediq, A. Afana, and M. Erol-Kantarci, 鈥淟arge language | models in wireless application design: In-context learning-enhanced au- | tomatic network intrusion detection,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2405.11002,
  L062: 鈥淢\鈥檈lange: Cost efficient large language model serving by exploiting | GPU heterogeneity,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.14527, 2024. | [16] B. Sun, Z. Huang, H. Zhao, W. Xiao, X. Zhang, Y. Li, and W. Lin,
  L068: 鈥淐ached model-as-a-resource: Provisioning large language model agents | for edge intelligence in space-air-ground integrated networks,鈥?arXiv | preprint arXiv:2403.05826, 2024.
  L072: resource management in edge learning: A joint pre-training and fine- | tuning design paradigm,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communica- | tions, vol. 24, no. 2, pp. 1584鈥?601, 2025.
  L080: [20] Z. Lyu, M. Xiao, J. Xu, M. Skoglund, and M. Di Renzo, 鈥淭he larger the | merrier? efficient large ai model inference in wireless edge networks,鈥?| arXiv preprint arXiv:2505.09214, 2025.
  L083: [21] Y. Chen, R. Li, X. Yu, Z. Zhao, and H. Zhang, 鈥淎daptive layer | splitting for wireless LLM inference in edge computing: A model-based | reinforcement learning approach,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2406.02616,
  L087: [22] S. Ohta and T. Nishio, 鈥溛?split: A privacy-preserving split com- | puting framework for cloud-powered generative AI,鈥?arXiv preprint | arXiv:2310.14651, 2023.
  L090: [23] D. Wen, P. Liu, G. Zhu, Y. Shi, J. Xu, Y. C. Eldar, and S. Cui, | 鈥淭ask-oriented sensing, computation, and communication integration for | multi-device edge ai,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications,
  L091: 鈥淭ask-oriented sensing, computation, and communication integration for | multi-device edge ai,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, | vol. 23, no. 3, pp. 2486鈥?502, 2023.
  L093: vol. 23, no. 3, pp. 2486鈥?502, 2023. | [24] F. You, H. Du, K. Huang, and A. Jamalipour, 鈥淛ppo: Joint power and | prompt optimization for accelerated large language model services,鈥?
  L112: tions on Communications, vol. 61, no. 8, pp. 3541鈥?551, 2013. | [30] T. Zhang, K. Zhu, and J. Wang, 鈥淓nergy-efficient mode selection | and resource allocation for D2D-enabled heterogeneous networks: A
  L114: and resource allocation for D2D-enabled heterogeneous networks: A | deep reinforcement learning approach,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless | Communications, vol. 20, no. 2, pp. 1175鈥?187, 2020.
  L120: no. 4, pp. 3890鈥?904, 2019. | [32] T. Zhang, K. Zhu, and J. Wang, 鈥淓nergy-efficient mode selection | and resource allocation for D2D-enabled heterogeneous networks: A
  L122: and resource allocation for D2D-enabled heterogeneous networks: A | deep reinforcement learning approach,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless | Communications, vol. 20, no. 2, pp. 1175鈥?187, 2021.
  L126: reinforcement learning for efficient content caching in mobile D2D | networks,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications, vol. 18, | no. 3, pp. 1610鈥?622, 2019.
  L137: C. G. Brinton, 鈥淔ederated split learning with joint personalization- | generalization for inference-stage optimization in wireless edge net- | works,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing, vol. 23, no. 6, pp.
  L141: [37] N. Garg, M. Sellathurai, V. Bhatia, B. Bharath, and T. Ratnarajah, | 鈥淥nline content popularity prediction and learning in wireless edge | caching,鈥?IEEE Transactions on Communications, vol. 68, no. 2, pp.
  L146: based bayesian method for content popularity prediction in edge-caching | networks,鈥?in 2019 IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking | Conference (WCNC).
  L153: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
-- page 16 --
  L010: [42] M. Sun, X. Xu, Y. Huang, Q. Wu, X. Tao, and P. Zhang, 鈥淩esource | management for computation offloading in D2D-aided wireless powered | mobile-edge computing networks,鈥?IEEE Internet of Things Journal,
  L013: vol. 8, no. 10, pp. 8005鈥?020, 2020. | [43] M. Finlayson, X. Ren, and S. Swayamdipta, 鈥淟ogits of api-protected | llms leak proprietary information,鈥?arXiv preprint arXiv:2403.09539,
  L021: content may change prior to final publication. Citation information: DOI 10.1109/TMC.2025.3608303 | 漏 2025 IEEE. All rights reserved, including rights for text and data mining and training of artificial intelligence and similar technologies. Personal use is permitted, | but republication/redistribution requires IEEE permission. See https://www.ieee.org/publications/rights/index.html for more information.
